<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- This is a WordPress eXtended RSS file generated by WordPress as an export of your site. -->
<!-- It contains information about your site's posts, pages, comments, categories, and other content. -->
<!-- You may use this file to transfer that content from one site to another. -->
<!-- This file is not intended to serve as a complete backup of your site. -->

<!-- To import this information into a WordPress site follow these steps: -->
<!-- 1. Log in to that site as an administrator. -->
<!-- 2. Go to Tools: Import in the WordPress admin panel. -->
<!-- 3. Install the "WordPress" importer from the list. -->
<!-- 4. Activate & Run Importer. -->
<!-- 5. Upload this file using the form provided on that page. -->
<!-- 6. You will first be asked to map the authors in this export file to users -->
<!--    on the site. For each author, you may choose to map to an -->
<!--    existing user on the site or to create a new user. -->
<!-- 7. WordPress will then import each of the posts, pages, comments, categories, etc. -->
<!--    contained in this file into your site. -->

<!-- generator="WordPress/4.9.8" created="2018-08-10 19:01" -->
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"
>

<channel>
	<title>Entrena</title>
	<link>https://entrena.fi</link>
	<description>Strength training for Aesthetic Group Gymnastics</description>
	<pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2018 19:01:02 +0000</pubDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<wp:wxr_version>1.2</wp:wxr_version>
	<wp:base_site_url>https://entrena.fi</wp:base_site_url>
	<wp:base_blog_url>https://entrena.fi</wp:base_blog_url>

	<wp:author><wp:author_id>3</wp:author_id><wp:author_login><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></wp:author_login><wp:author_email><![CDATA[sergionavadijo@gmail.com]]></wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Sergio Navadijo]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Sergio]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Navadijo]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>


	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9.8</generator>
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">130584660</site>
	<item>
		<title>WHY ARE THERE SO MANY INJURIES AND WHAT TO DO ABOUT IT</title>
		<link>https://entrena.fi/why-injuries/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 23:42:14 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://entrena.fi/?p=28790</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[et_pb_section bb_built="1" specialty="off" _builder_version="3.2.2"][et_pb_row _builder_version="3.0.96"][et_pb_column type="4_4"][et_pb_text admin_label="blog post model" max_width="560px" text_line_height_last_edited="on|phone" use_border_color="off" header_font_size="40px" text_font_size="16" text_line_height="1.6em" text_line_height_tablet="1.7em" header_text_color="#0c71c3" background_position="top_left" background_repeat="repeat" background_size="initial" _builder_version="3.2.2" text_font="Verdana||||||||" text_font_size_last_edited="on|phone" header_font_size_last_edited="on|desktop"]

From acute and chronic low back injuries to knee pain and ankle sprains, no Aesthetic Group Gymnastics team is unfamiliar with injuries.

Look closely at any given team, and you will realize that 3 to 4 girls are injured almost year round.

Coaches want the girls ready for next competition and don’t want to wait any longer.

Gymnasts rush getting back to training because being a teenager and having patience don't go well together.

Here are some of the reasons why AGG has so many injuries:

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Some coaches lack education. </strong></h3>
The far majority of coaches decided one day that they like gymnastics, competed in their teenage years, and later decided that it would be fun to coach the sport that they love.

Maybe they even went to a 3-month coach education to complement their practical experience.

Compare this to the “money” sports: football, basketball or ice hockey.

More often than not, you need a 4-year degree in sports science and two years of master studies in a sports specialty to be considered for a position on the team as a biomechanist, physiotherapist, strength coach or data analyst.

I will agree that practical experience is better than academic knowledge, but to ensure good coaching you need to have both.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Not everyone is built for AGG. </strong></h3>
In Finland, there’s this idea that everyone should be able to do the sport that they like and have access to it: sports for everybody.

I agree 100% with this philosophy, but here’s the catch: competitive sports are different.

While I am all in for financial support so that everyone can do sports, I’m not so convinced about everyone being “built” to compete in AGG.

I am not talking about the higher levels, not the lower divisions (kilpasarja in Finland).

A specific hip structure is required to be able to perform gymnastics skills at the elite level.

Most spines don’t tolerate rotation and extension very well, and a certain degree of joint hypermobility is required for advanced movements.

On top of this, if the coaches didn’t do an excellent job with flexibility training when the gymnasts were very young, the body will pay the price.

Lack of mobility at the upper back, hips, and ankles will result in low back pain and knee problems.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>They specialize too early. </strong></h3>
Specializing in on sport too early has been shown time and time again to increase the risk of injury and psychological stress <em>(Jayanthi, Pinkham, Dugas, Patrick, &amp; Labella, 2013).</em>

Sports specialization isn’t recommended at least until puberty is reached.

However, in gymnastics, like in other aesthetic sports, more hours of sports specific training and at an earlier age are required to reach peak performance in the late teens or early 20’s.

Compare this to strength or endurance sports where peak performance is reached at late 20’s or early 30’s.

Furthermore, let’s not forget that flexibility decreases faster than any other physical ability.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>What you can do about it</strong></h3>
<strong>Strength Train.</strong>

A review of 25 studies in 2013 that included a total of 26610 athletes concluded that <a href="http://bjsm.bmj.com/content/early/2013/10/07/bjsports-2013-092538.short?rss=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">strength training reduced sports injuries to less than 1/3.</a>

In addition, strength training almost halved overuse injuries <em>(Lauersen, Bertelsen, &amp; Andersen, 2014</em>).

Culturally, gymnastics is often anchored to obsolete myths about getting bulky and lifting weights being a bad thing for children.

Not only will it notably reduce injuries but it will help you jump more <em>(Piazza et al., 2014).</em>

Perfect technique and adequate progression is a must, and strength training needs to be done at least 2 to 3 times a week year round.

&nbsp;

<strong>Educate yourself.</strong>

Unless we want to keep on getting hurt, we need to transition to professional coaching.

I am not saying that everyone needs to have a degree in sports science.

However, if you can’t describe what the muscles involved in gymnastic skills do, it is unlikely that you will be able to develop them.

Often what coaches think will help gain mobility and strength and the upper back is damaging the low back and doing nothing for performance.

&nbsp;

<strong>Putting it all together:</strong>
<ul>
 	<li>Coaches need to understand what exercises are adequate for the level of each gymnast.</li>
 	<li>Asking for an exercise list from the physiotherapist or the strength coach won’t solve the problem.</li>
 	<li>Spend time educating yourself, don't just ask somebody for exercises.</li>
 	<li>Individualization of training is a must: each gymnast has particular needs, and you may cause damage with standard exercises.</li>
</ul>
&nbsp;

<strong>References:</strong>

<em>Jayanthi, N., Pinkham, C., Dugas, L., Patrick, B., &amp; Labella, C. (2013). Sports specialization in young athletes: evidence-based recommendations. Sports Health, 5(3), 251–7. </em>doi<em>:10.1177/1941738112464626</em>

<em>Lauersen, J. B., Bertelsen, D. M., &amp; Andersen, L. B. (2014). The effectiveness of exercise interventions to prevent sports injuries: a systematic review and meta-analysis of </em>randomised<em> controlled trials. British Journal of Sports Medicine, 48(11), 871–7. </em>doi<em>:10.1136/bjsports-2013-092538</em>

<em>Myer, G. D., Jayanthi, N., DiFiori, J. P., Faigenbaum, A. D., Kiefer, A. W., Logerstedt, D., &amp; Micheli, L. J. (2016). Sports Specialization, Part II: Alternative Solutions to Early </em>Sport<em> Specialization in Youth Athletes. Sports Health, 8(1), 65–73. </em>doi<em>:10.1177/1941738115614811</em>

<em>Piazza, M., Battaglia, C., Fiorilli, G., Innocenti, G., Iuliano, E., Aquino, G., … Di Cagno, A. (2014). Effects of resistance training on jumping performance in pre-adolescent rhythmic gymnasts: a randomized controlled study. Italian Journal of Anatomy and Embryology = Archivio Italiano Di Anatomia Ed Embriologia, 119(1), 10–9. Retrieved from http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25345071</em>

[/et_pb_text][/et_pb_column][/et_pb_row][/et_pb_section]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[AGG injuries are common, but they don't have to be.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>28790</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-03-12 01:42:14]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-03-11 23:42:14]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[why-injuries]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="injuries"><![CDATA[Injuries]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_monarch_override]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_color]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[#ffffff]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[light]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_show_title]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_post_hide_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_page_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[et_full_width_page]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_side_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[off]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_use_builder]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_ab_stats_refresh_interval]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hourly]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_old_content]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<p>In this post you will learn <strong>why there are so many injuries in Aesthetic Group Gymnastics</strong> and<strong> what to do about it</strong>.</p><p>Let’s jump in:</p><p><em>From acute and chronic low back injuries to knee pain and ankle sprains, no Aesthetic Group Gymnastics team is unfamiliar with injuries. </em></p><p><em>Look closely at any given team and often you will realize that 3 to 4 girls in each team are injured almost year round. </em></p><p><em>Coaches want the girls ready for next competition and don’t want to wait any longer. </em></p><p><em>Gymnasts rush getting back to </em>trainings<em> because being a teenager and thinking long term are antagonist terms. </em></p><p><em>Here are some of the reasons why AGG is ridden with injuries and -possibly- more than most other sports:</em></p><p><strong>Coaches lack education. </strong>The far majority of coaches decided one day that they like gymnastics, competed in their teenage years, and later decided that it would be fun to coach the sport that they love.</p><p>Maybe they even went to some sort of 3-month coach education to complement their practical experience.</p><p>Compare this to the “money” sports: football, basketball, ice hockey.</p><p>More often than not, you need a 4-year degree in sports science and 2 years of master studies in a sports specialty to be considered for a position on the team as a bio-mechanist, physiotherapist, strength coach or data analyst.</p><p><strong>It’s not for everyone</strong>. I get it. In Finland, there’s this idea that everyone should be able to do the sport that they like and have access to it: sports for everybody.</p><p>I agree 100% with this philosophy, but here’s the catch: competitive sports are different.</p><p>While I am all in for financial support so that everyone can do sports, I’m not so convinced about everyone being “built” to compete in gymnastics in a healthy manner.</p><p>I am not talking about the low divisions (kilpasarja in Finnish), but about the higher levels.</p><p>A certain hip structure is required to be able to perform gymnastics skills.</p><p>Most spines don’t tolerate rotation and extension very well, and a certain degree of joint hypermobility is required for advanced movements.</p><p>If your overhead squat looks <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7hZ-rUYH3iU" target="_blank" rel="noopener">like this</a>, maybe gymnastics is not the best option.</p><p>Not to mention that if the coaches didn’t do an excellent job with flexibility training when the gymnasts were very young, the body will pay the price.</p><p>Lack of mobility at the upper back, hips and ankles will result in low back pain and knee problems.</p><p>It is just not worth to suffer a variety of back problems at an early age when we only have one spine for the rest of our lives.</p><div id="attachment_2426" class="wp-caption alignnone"><p><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/n-bnb.jpg" rel="attachment wp-att-2426"><img class="wp-image-2426 size-full" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/n-bnb.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/n-bnb.jpg 630w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/n-bnb-300x168.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/n-bnb-610x341.jpg 610w" alt="While everyone should have access to sports, not every spine and hip structure is built for gymnastics." width="630" height="352" /></a></p><p class="wp-caption-text">While everyone should have access to sports, not every spine and hip structure is built for gymnastics.</p></div><p> </p><p><strong>The entry level is high.</strong> While anybody can throw a basketball without getting hurt, the same is not true for gymnastics.</p><p>Think about the most basic gymnastic skills and jumps: you need to have extreme flexibility, motor control, power and balance to be able to do them.</p><p>It can take years of training to be able to do the most fundamental movements, which can be discouraging.</p><p>Be ready to invest a huge part of life in gymnastics.</p><p><strong>It is a skill-based sport</strong>, not a decision-making sport.</p><p>It all comes down to this: Repetition work.</p><p>Leaving general preparation aside, it’s the amount of repetitions of a certain skill or specific choreography what will get you further.</p><p>This leads to overuse injuries: knee tendonitis, stress fractures, spine degeneration, you name it.</p><p><strong>Early Specialization.</strong> Specializing in on sport too early <strong><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24427397" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has been shown</a></strong> time and time again to increase risk of injury and psychological stress (Jayanthi, Pinkham, Dugas, Patrick, & Labella, 2013).</p><p>Sports specialization isn’t recommended at least until puberty is reached.</p><p>However, in gymnastics, like in other aesthetic sports, more hours of sports specific training and at an earlier age are required to reach peak performance in the late teens or early 20’s.</p><p>Compare this to strength or endurance sports where peak performance is reached at late 20’s or early 30’s.</p><p>Furthermore, let’s not forget that flexibility decreases faster than any other physical ability.</p><p>All this forces teenage gymnasts to train and behave like adult professional athletes.</p><p><strong>Growing years</strong>. Gymnasts are performing skills in extreme ranges of motion without the strength to control their limbs and body posture.</p><p>Combine the lack of strength training in most teams with a body and a nervous system that is trying to adapt to the new length of arms and legs.</p><p>This results in very poor motor control and balance, increasing the risk of injury.</p><p>Continue reading and let’s see what we can do to reduce the injury epidemic and make the world of gymnastics a better place.</p><p><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/hh.jpg" rel="attachment wp-att-2434"><img class="alignnone wp-image-2434 size-full" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/hh.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 889px) 100vw, 889px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/hh.jpg 889w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/hh-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/hh-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/hh-610x407.jpg 610w" alt="joukkue" width="889" height="593" /></a></p><h3> </h3><h3>How to change things for the better:</h3><p><strong>Strength Train</strong>.</p><p>A review of 25 studies in 2013 that included a total of 26610 athletes concluded that <strong><a href="http://bjsm.bmj.com/content/early/2013/10/07/bjsports-2013-092538.short?rss=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">strength training reduced sports injuries to less than 1/3</a>.</strong></p><p>On this topic, I<strong> </strong>strongly recommend reading<strong> <a href="http://coach.ninemsn.com.au/2016/03/18/17/22/why-kids-should-lift-weights" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this article.</a></strong></p><p>In addition, strength training almost halved overuse injuries (Lauersen, Bertelsen, & Andersen, 2014) .</p><p>Culturally, gymnastics is often anchored to obsolete myths about getting bulky and lifting weights being a bad thing for children.</p><p>Not only will it notably reduce injuries but it will help you <strong><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25345071" target="_blank" rel="noopener">jump more</a></strong>, as we know from this study with gymnasts (Piazza et al., 2014).</p><p>Perfect technique and adequate progression is a must, and strength training needs to be done at least 2 to 3 times a week year round.</p><p>Read more on this <strong><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/2015/09/12/agg-basics-part-3-strength/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in my past article</a></strong>.</p><div id="attachment_2429" class="wp-caption alignnone"><p><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/DSC04732.jpg" rel="attachment wp-att-2429"><img class="wp-image-2429 size-large" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/DSC04732-722x1024.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 722px) 100vw, 722px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/DSC04732-722x1024.jpg 722w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/DSC04732-212x300.jpg 212w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/DSC04732-768x1089.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/DSC04732-610x865.jpg 610w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/DSC04732-1080x1531.jpg 1080w" alt="With perfect technique and the right load, the squat is an excellent strength exercise for gymnastics." width="722" height="1024" /></a></p><p class="wp-caption-text">With perfect technique and the right load, the squat is an excellent strength exercise for gymnastics. Photo: Petri Vilhunen.</p></div><p> </p><p><strong>Education systems.</strong></p><p>Unless we want to keep on getting hurt, we need to slowly transition to professional coaching.</p><p>I am not saying that everyone needs to have a degree in sports science.</p><p>However, if you can’t describe what are the muscles involved in the basic gymnastic skills as well as their functions, it is unlikely that you will be able to develop them.</p><p><strong>Don’t copy what others are doing</strong>.</p><p>Often what coaches think will help gain mobility and strength and the upper back is actually damaging the low back and doing nothing for performance.</p><p>Here’s a bad example from artistic gymnastics:</p><div class="fluid-width-video-wrapper"><iframe id="fitvid0" class="youtube-player" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/j_qSyfiHibs?version=3&rel=1&fs=1&autohide=2&showsearch=0&showinfo=1&iv_load_policy=1&wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></div><p> </p><p><strong>Things to remember:</strong></p><p>There aren’t good or bad exercises and it all depends on the context.</p><p>Coaches need to understand what exercises are adequate for the level of each gymnast.</p><p>Asking for an exercise list from the physiotherapist or the strength coach won’t solve the problem.</p><p>Spend time educating yourself: learn how to fish, don’t just buy the fish.</p><p>Each gymnast has very specific needs and you may cause damage with standard recommendations.</p><p>Individualization of training is a must.</p><p><strong>Load management.</strong> We have known now for more than 50 years that in order to reach peak performance, the weeks and months before a competition intensity needs to increase and volume needs to decrease.</p><p>What we see in gymnastics is an increase in intensity AND volume, in part due to the anxiety and fear of not having rehearsed enough.</p><p>This is a recipe for disaster that often leads to injuries in the last weeks before the competition.</p><p>Instead, coaches should keep volume high and intensity low far from the competition, while slowly transitioning to more intensity and less volume the closer the competition is.</p><p>Read <strong><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/2015/07/02/agg-basics-part-1-training-volume/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">my past article</a></strong> on this matter.</p><p><strong>Recovery.</strong></p><p>When was the last time you asked your gymnasts how are they sleeping?</p><p>What are their habits before going to bed?</p><p>A simple weekly questionnaire can help coaches see why some girls come to practice with red eyes or why they have no energies.</p><p>Education about sleep hygiene can go a long way. Check out <strong><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/2015/07/06/agg-basics-part-2-recovery/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this article</a></strong>.</p><p><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/relax-955798.jpg" rel="attachment wp-att-2436"><img class="alignnone wp-image-2436 size-large" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/relax-955798-1024x768.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/relax-955798-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/relax-955798-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/relax-955798-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/relax-955798-610x458.jpg 610w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/relax-955798-1080x810.jpg 1080w" alt="relax" width="1024" height="768" /></a></p><p><strong>Nutrition.</strong></p><p>Most of us are fat, so we don’t dare to demand athletic body composition to the gymnasts.</p><p>We are afraid of causing eating disorders.</p><p>We don’t weigh our gymnast because that would be a horrible thing. However, scales are freely available at home.</p><p>Put a 5kg backpack on your back and jump 150 times. How do your knees and back feel?</p><p>This is what many gymnasts go through.</p><p>Wanna stay healthy? Keep a balanced diet. No need to go crazy.</p><p>Just avoid refined foods and eat small portions while eating lean protein.</p><p>Knees and back will thank you.</p><h3><strong>In conclusion</strong></h3><p>Is it possible to remain injury free? No.</p><p>But certainly the risk can be mitigated with careful monitoring and management of training load and recovery.</p><p>Injuries need to be taken very seriously, especially the ones around the spine.</p><p>Low back pain can’t be taken as “normal”, and we need to evaluate if the reason for pain is poor training methods, poor skill level or simply not being built for the sport.</p><p>Health first, performance second.</p><p>Please share this article so others may benefit.</p><p>Jayanthi, N., Pinkham, C., Dugas, L., Patrick, B., & Labella, C. (2013). Sports specialization in young athletes: evidence-based recommendations. <em>Sports Health</em>, <em>5</em>(3), 251–7. doi:10.1177/1941738112464626</p><p>Lauersen, J. B., Bertelsen, D. M., & Andersen, L. B. (2014). The effectiveness of exercise interventions to prevent sports injuries: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials. <em>British Journal of Sports Medicine</em>, <em>48</em>(11), 871–7. doi:10.1136/bjsports-2013-092538</p><p>Myer, G. D., Jayanthi, N., DiFiori, J. P., Faigenbaum, A. D., Kiefer, A. W., Logerstedt, D., & Micheli, L. J. (2016). Sports Specialization, Part II: Alternative Solutions to Early Sport Specialization in Youth Athletes. <em>Sports Health</em>, <em>8</em>(1), 65–73. doi:10.1177/1941738115614811</p><p>Piazza, M., Battaglia, C., Fiorilli, G., Innocenti, G., Iuliano, E., Aquino, G., … Di Cagno, A. (2014). Effects of resistance training on jumping performance in pre-adolescent rhythmic gymnasts: a randomized controlled study. <em>Italian Journal of Anatomy and Embryology = Archivio Italiano Di Anatomia Ed Embriologia</em>, <em>119</em>(1), 10–9. Retrieved from http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25345071</p><p> </p>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_enable_shortcode_tracking]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_custom_css]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_oembed_9a48449f6ad87e5cc85bc184d4a231f9]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[{{unknown}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jetpack_related_posts_cache]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:32:"fe368e571123892bf7f008fb2a5317a6";a:2:{s:7:"expires";i:1533503059;s:7:"payload";a:3:{i:0;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29355;}i:1;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29241;}i:2;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29257;}}}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_thumbnail_id]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[29957]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_show_author_inthis_post]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[author_default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_builder_version]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BB|Divi|3.2.2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[et_enqueued_post_fonts]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:2:{s:6:"family";a:1:{s:21:"et-gf-source-sans-pro";s:100:"Source+Sans+Pro:200,200italic,300,300italic,regular,italic,600,600italic,700,700italic,900,900italic";}s:6:"subset";a:7:{i:0;s:8:"cyrillic";i:1;s:5:"greek";i:2;s:10:"vietnamese";i:3;s:5:"latin";i:4;s:9:"greek-ext";i:5;s:9:"latin-ext";i:6;s:12:"cyrillic-ext";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_wp_old_slug]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a-g-g-basics-part-4-injuries]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>10 THINGS YOU SHOULD DO TO AVOID KNEE PAIN</title>
		<link>https://entrena.fi/10-things-you-should-do-to-avoid-knee-pain/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 23:43:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://entrena.fi/?p=28792</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[et_pb_section bb_built="1" specialty="off" _builder_version="3.2.2"][et_pb_row _builder_version="3.0.96"][et_pb_column type="4_4"][et_pb_text admin_label="blog post model" max_width="560px" text_line_height_last_edited="on|phone" use_border_color="off" header_font_size="40px" text_font_size="16" text_line_height="1.6em" text_line_height_tablet="1.7em" header_text_color="#0c71c3" background_position="top_left" background_repeat="repeat" background_size="initial" _builder_version="3.2.2" text_font="Verdana||||||||" text_font_size_last_edited="on|phone" header_font_size_last_edited="on|desktop"]

Here are a few key points that we can do to reduce knee problems in gymnasts:

&nbsp;

<strong>1. Improve ankle range of motion.</strong>

Typically, gymnasts present a lack of ankle dorsiflexion, as most of their sport specific skills happen in plantar flexion.

The lack of ankle dorsiflexion and internal rotation on the ankle joint will be compensated by the knee, resulting in pain and sometimes serious injuries.

A simple set of exercises with this purpose will benefit you greatly.

&nbsp;

<strong>2. Increase glute medius activation.</strong>

The glute medius primarily does hip abduction, and it is vital in lateral movements and single leg stability.

A weak glute medius means trouble for your knees.

One way to solve this adding exercises like banded monster walks and hip airplanes during warmups.

&nbsp;

<strong>3. Improve motor control.</strong>

Every gymnast should be able to perform basic movements like squats, deadlifts and jumps without compensating with lumbar lordosis or valgus at the knee.

If they can’t do the most basic movements right, don’t expect them to stay injury free when practicing complicated moves like AGG skills.

&nbsp;

<strong>4. Improve hip mobility.</strong>

Lack of range of motion at the hips is a threat both for the knees and for the lumbar spine.

Stretch the hip flexors, hip extensors, hip internal rotators and hip external rotators.

Every day. Every session. All the time.

&nbsp;

<strong>5. Strength train.</strong>

Mobility without stability is a recipe for disaster.

Don’t be that gymnast that is afraid of strength training because you think it’s dangerous or because it’s going to make you muscular: Not doing strength training is dangerous.

&nbsp;

<strong>6. Do more posterior chain work.</strong>

Hip thrusts, deadlifts, single leg deadlifts are your best friend.

Quad dominant gymnasts will have a predisposition for knee tendonitis and other related problems.

Work on the muscles that you don’t see in the mirror!

&nbsp;

<strong>7. Before going to the physio, think twice about the way you are training.</strong>

The physio can’t correct poor training practice.

Physical therapy is an excellent complement to attenuate symptoms but never to solve the root of training-related problems.

&nbsp;

<strong>8. Go to the doctor.</strong>

If you train correctly and knee pain doesn’t improve, find a good sports doctor.

Coaches and physical therapists can’t scan your knee to see if the joint structures are damaged.

The doctor is always the first professional you should visit.

&nbsp;

<strong>9. Use common sense.</strong>

If an exercise hurts, don’t do it: Don’t ignore bad pain.

More often than not it’s your own body warning you that something is not right.

&nbsp;

<strong>10. Lose fat and keep it off.</strong>

Notice I said fat, not muscle.

Stay in shape, otherwise, your joints will have to absorb very high forces in every landing, increasing injury risk.

[/et_pb_text][et_pb_social_media_follow follow_button="on" _builder_version="3.2.2" border_radii="on|100%|100%|100%|100%" saved_tabs="all" global_module="29607"][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="instagram" url="https://www.instagram.com/agg_entrena" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#517fa4" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on"]

&lt;p&gt;Instagram&lt;/p&gt;

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="facebook" url="https://www.facebook.com/entrenafi/" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#3b5998" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px" background_video_pause_outside_viewport="on" box_shadow_style="none"]

Facebook

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="youtube" url="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnr5AS5uScFE2hmcGBsJitA" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#a82400" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px"]

Youtube

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][/et_pb_social_media_follow][/et_pb_column][/et_pb_row][/et_pb_section]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Factors to consider when dealing with knee problems.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>28792</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-03-12 01:43:36]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-03-11 23:43:36]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[10-things-you-should-do-to-avoid-knee-pain]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="injuries"><![CDATA[Injuries]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_monarch_override]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_color]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[#ffffff]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[light]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_show_title]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_post_hide_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_page_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[et_full_width_page]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_side_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[off]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_use_builder]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_ab_stats_refresh_interval]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hourly]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_old_content]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<p>If you, your daughter or your athletes do aesthetic group gymnastics, the chances are that they have or have had knee pain at some point.</p><p>Here are a few key points that we can do to reduce knee problems in gymnasts:</p><p>1. Improve ankle range of motion.</p><p>Typically, gymnasts present a lack of ankle dorsiflexion, as most of their sport specific skills happen in plantar flexion.</p><p>The lack of ankle dorsiflexion and internal rotation on the ankle joint will be compensated by the knee, resulting in pain and sometimes serious injuries.</p><p>2. Increase glute medius activation.</p><p>The glute medius primarily does hip abduction, and it is vital in lateral movements and single leg stability.</p><p>A weak glute medius means trouble for your knees.</p><p>3. Improve motor control.</p><p>Every gymnast should be able to perform basic movements like squats, deadlifts and jumps without compensating with lumbar lordosis or valgus at the knees.</p><p>If they can’t do the most basic movements right, don’t expect them to stay injury free when practicing complicated moves like AGG skills.</p><p>4. Improve hip mobility. </p><p>Lack of range of motion at the hips is a threat both for the knees and for the lumbar spine.</p><p>Stretch the hip flexors, extensors, internal and external rotators.</p><p>Every day. Every session. All the time.</p><p>5. Strength train. </p><p>Mobility without stability is a recipe for disaster.</p><p>Don’t be that gymnast that is afraid of strength training because you think it’s dangerous or because it’s going to make you muscular: Not doing strength training is dangerous.</p><p>6. Do more posterior chain work. </p><p>Hip thrusts, deadlifts, single leg deadlifts are your best friend.</p><p>Quad dominant gymnasts will have a predisposition for knee tendonitis and other related problems.</p><p>Work on the muscles that you don’t see in the mirror!</p><p>7. Before going to the physio, think twice about the way you are training. </p><p>The physio can’t correct poor training practice, just like a pill doesn’t cure sickness.</p><p>Physical therapy is an excellent complement to attenuate symptoms but never to solve the root of training-related problems.</p><p>8. Go to the doctor. </p><p>We have good social health care in Finland.</p><p>If you train correctly and knee pain doesn’t improve, find a good sports doctor.</p><p>Coaches and physical therapists can’t scan your knee to see if the structures are healthy.</p><p>It might not sound sexy, but the doctor is still your best bet.</p><p>9. Use common sense. </p><p>If an exercise hurts, don’t do it: Don’t ignore bad pain.</p><p>More often than not it’s your own body warning you that something is not right.</p><p>It doesn’t warn twice.</p><p>10. Lose fat and keep it off. </p><p>Notice I said fat, not muscle.</p><p>Keep a food diary.</p><p>You’ll be surprised how little protein and how much carbs and total calories you are eating.</p>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_enable_shortcode_tracking]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_custom_css]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jetpack_related_posts_cache]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:32:"8f6677c9d6b0f903e98ad32ec61f8deb";a:2:{s:7:"expires";i:1533080286;s:7:"payload";a:3:{i:0;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28790;}i:1;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29355;}i:2;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29333;}}}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_thumbnail_id]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[29958]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_show_author_inthis_post]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[author_default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_builder_version]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BB|Divi|3.2.2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[et_enqueued_post_fonts]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:2:{s:6:"family";a:1:{s:21:"et-gf-source-sans-pro";s:100:"Source+Sans+Pro:200,200italic,300,300italic,regular,italic,600,600italic,700,700italic,900,900italic";}s:6:"subset";a:7:{i:0;s:8:"cyrillic";i:1;s:5:"greek";i:2;s:10:"vietnamese";i:3;s:5:"latin";i:4;s:9:"greek-ext";i:5;s:9:"latin-ext";i:6;s:12:"cyrillic-ext";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_wp_old_slug]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[10-things-you-should-do-to-avoid-knee-pain-in-gymnastics]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>HOW GLORIA JUNIOR INCREASED THEIR JUMPS 20%</title>
		<link>https://entrena.fi/the-secrets-of-jumping/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 23:45:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://entrena.fi/?p=28796</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[et_pb_section bb_built="1" specialty="off" _builder_version="3.2.2"][et_pb_row _builder_version="3.0.96"][et_pb_column type="4_4"][et_pb_text admin_label="blog post model" max_width="560px" text_line_height_last_edited="on|phone" use_border_color="off" header_font_size="40px" text_font_size="16" text_line_height="1.6em" text_line_height_tablet="1.7em" header_text_color="#0c71c3" background_position="top_left" background_repeat="repeat" background_size="initial" _builder_version="3.2.2" text_font="Verdana||||||||" text_font_size_last_edited="on|phone" header_font_size_last_edited="on|desktop"]
<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_0 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left">
<div class="et_pb_text_inner">
<h3><strong>This is how we trained:</strong></h3>
<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xpM0pqmNR9Q" width="1663" height="734" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe>

</div>
</div>
<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_1 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left">
<h4></h4>
<h3><strong>Take home points:</strong></h3>
<ul>
 	<li>The average jump height of team Gloria Junior improved 20% (6,11 centimeters).</li>
 	<li>They did this in a five-month period, with one strength training session per week plus a series of exercises to be implemented during their regular gymnastics training.</li>
 	<li>We used a mix of squatting, deadlifting and pressing movements with a particular emphasis on glutes and core.</li>
 	<li>Plyometrics and jumping and landing technique was an important part of the program.</li>
 	<li>A significant percentage of the improvement can be attributed to the gymnasts still being in a growing phase (they are 13 to 15 years old).</li>
 	<li>Another factor for this big improvement is that they had no previous history of strength training, which elicits a high initial response.</li>
</ul>
&nbsp;
<div class="et_pb_text_inner">
<h3><strong>Here are the Top 3 Jumpers:</strong></h3>
<a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/top3.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-24622" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/top3-300x171.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 370px) 100vw, 370px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/top3-300x171.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/top3-768x439.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/top3-610x349.jpg 610w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/top3.jpg 826w" alt="top3" width="370" height="211" /></a>
<h4></h4>
<h3><strong>The details</strong></h3>
The benefits of getting strong will transfer to jumping, but also include enhancements in general sports skills as well as decreases in risk of injury (Suchomel, Nimphius, &amp; Stone, 2016).

To develop jumps in a young gymnast, we need a combination of explosive movements and heavy-resistance strength training (Maffiuletti et al., 2016).

In the past, the times when I have failed to improve the jumping height of athletes, it’s been due to these 2 things:

<strong>Lack of consistency</strong>. You can’t strength train six weeks, stop training, train another six weeks, stop again and expect to increase or even maintain jumping power.

Strength and power need to be developed and maintained as high as possible year round.

<strong>Poor Nutrition</strong>.  Fat doesn’t fly.

Any body mass that is not directly contributing to propulsive forces (in other words, body fat) is hindering your power.

Overweight gymnasts won’t jump high.

No training system will overcome these two premises.

With Gloria Junior, I have had the opportunity to work for five months on a consistent basis.

This way, we eliminated constraint number one (lack of consistency).

When it comes to bodyweight, they are visibly lean.

This eliminates the second constraint (sub-optimal fat levels).

Now I can strength train them and help them get the results they want.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Data analysis</strong></h3>
We tested a countermovement jump using a validated contact platform from Chronojump.

Here are the results of the test and the re-test:

<a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-24584" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo-300x297.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 525px) 100vw, 525px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo-300x297.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo-768x760.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo-610x604.jpg 610w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo.jpg 904w" alt="data1" width="525" height="520" /></a>

To see the jump scores, look into the column that says “ABK (Cm)” in blue, and the column that says “ABK (Cm)” in yellow (test and re-test).

Move on to the table below.

You can see the average score of the team (mean), the standard deviation (SD) and the best and worst jumps (Min and Max).

For averages, I didn’t take into account the athletes in red, as they missed one of the tests due to injury/sickness.

I have also included the z-scores, which is a measure that says how good each gymnast can jump compared to the average of the team.

A z-score above 0 means you can jump more than the average, and a z-score under 0 means you jump less than the team average.

While you could already see this directly from the jump height in centimeters, it is a handy measure to deeper analyze the data.

Keep reading.

The next step was to visualize the improvements in absolute change (how many centimeters they improved) as well as in relative change (what percentage of improvement).

I also added each individual and mean z-scores.

You can see this in the two right columns. Please click on the table to see it better:

</div>
</div>
<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_2 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left">
<div class="et_pb_text_inner"></div>
</div>
<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_3 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left">
<div class="et_pb_text_inner">

[caption id="attachment_30089" align="alignnone" width="990"]<a href="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/sdf-1.jpg"><img class="wp-image-30089 size-full" src="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/sdf-1.jpg" alt="" width="990" height="650" /></a> Click to enlarge[/caption]

Realize that factors like weight loss or weight gain, motivation, readiness, and wherein the menstrual cycle the athlete is all can affect test scores positively or negatively.

Results in tests are just an opportunity to see trends, not a definitive judgment in performance -leave that for competition time.

Now, let’s look now at correlations:

<a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/d.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-24587" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/d-300x97.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 492px) 100vw, 492px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/d-300x97.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/d-768x249.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/d-610x198.jpg 610w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/d.jpg 796w" alt="correlation" width="673" height="219" /></a>

Looking at the table above, we see almost no correlation between test and absolute and relative changes.

This means that <strong>both the gymnasts with high and low initial scores improved substantially</strong>.

As the gymnasts become more advanced athletes, it will be a lot harder to see improvements of this magnitude over time.

An excellent way to make the data easier to understand is to use scatter plots.

Below this paragraph, you can see a scatter plot of the initial test vs. the relative change or improvement.

The more on the left an athlete is, the less they jumped in the initial test.

The higher an athlete is, the more they improved regarding percentage change.

I also added a trend line, which is showing a non-significant skew towards low initial test scores having a more significant relative change.

[caption id="attachment_30090" align="alignnone" width="1167"]<a href="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/jump-test.jpg"><img class="wp-image-30090 size-full" src="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/jump-test.jpg" alt="" width="1167" height="630" /></a> click to enlarge[/caption]

Next one is a scatter plot of the relative change in z-scores.

[caption id="attachment_30091" align="alignnone" width="1237"]<a href="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/relative-change.jpg"><img class="wp-image-30091 size-full" src="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/relative-change.jpg" alt="" width="1237" height="618" /></a> click to enlarge[/caption]

Here we can see who improved the most compared to the average of the team (0 in the vertical axis):

</div>
</div>
<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_4 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left">
<div class="et_pb_text_inner">

Now, this is where it gets interesting.

I divided the gymnasts into <strong>high and low responders. </strong>

We can accomplish this by looking at the z-scores of the initial test and the relative change.

This way we end up with a very useful quadrant where we can rapidly see:
<ul>
 	<li>Gymnasts with a <strong>low initial ability that responded poorly</strong> to the training program.</li>
 	<li>Gymnasts with a <strong>low initial ability that responded well</strong> to the training program.</li>
 	<li>Gymnasts with a <strong>high initial ability that responded poorly</strong> to the training program.</li>
 	<li>Gymnasts with a <strong>high initial ability that responded well</strong> to the training program.</li>
</ul>
[caption id="attachment_30092" align="alignnone" width="1019"]<a href="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/quadrant-analysis.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-30092" src="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/quadrant-analysis.jpg" alt="" width="1019" height="641" /></a> click to enlarge[/caption]

This graph is very cool because it will allow us to <strong>individualize the training</strong>, dividing gymnasts into groups depending on their characteristics.

We need to change the training for some gymnasts while others can keep training in the same manner.

We also can decide how much strength training is necessary for each of them according to their response.

Some gymnasts can focus on gymnastics skills and less in strength while others should focus on strength and less on skills.

Again, these are just trends, and we have to be very careful when interpreting tests results.

But provided that we don’t make false conclusions, this is precious information.

With that said, I am confident in this approach.

Expect high-flying gymnasts next season

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>References:</strong></h3>
<em>Maffiuletti, N. A., Aagaard, P., Blazevich, A. J., Folland, J., Tillin, N., &amp; Duchateau, J. (2016). Rate of force development: physiological and methodological considerations. European Journal of Applied Physiology, 116(6), 1091–116. </em>doi<em>:10.1007/s00421-016-3346-6</em>

<em>Mladen </em>Janovic<em>. (n.d.). Complementary Training. Retrieved from www.complementarytraining.net</em>

<em>Suchomel, T. J., Nimphius, S., &amp; Stone, M. H. (2016). The Importance of Muscular Strength in Athletic Performance. Sports Medicine, 1–31. </em>doi<em>:10.1007/s40279-016-0486-0</em>

</div>
</div>
[/et_pb_text][et_pb_social_media_follow follow_button="on" _builder_version="3.2.2" border_radii="on|100%|100%|100%|100%" saved_tabs="all" global_module="29607"][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="instagram" url="https://www.instagram.com/agg_entrena" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#517fa4" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on"]

&lt;p&gt;Instagram&lt;/p&gt;

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="facebook" url="https://www.facebook.com/entrenafi/" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#3b5998" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px" background_video_pause_outside_viewport="on" box_shadow_style="none"]

Facebook

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="youtube" url="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnr5AS5uScFE2hmcGBsJitA" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#a82400" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px"]

Youtube

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][/et_pb_social_media_follow][/et_pb_column][/et_pb_row][/et_pb_section]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Strength training and data analysis to fly high.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>28796</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-03-12 01:45:58]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-03-11 23:45:58]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[the-secrets-of-jumping]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="strength"><![CDATA[Strength]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="jumps"><![CDATA[Jumps]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_monarch_override]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_color]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[#ffffff]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[light]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_show_title]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_post_hide_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_page_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[et_full_width_page]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_side_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[off]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_use_builder]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_ab_stats_refresh_interval]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hourly]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_old_content]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_0 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left"><div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p><strong>Take home points:</strong></p><ul><li>The average jump height of team Gloria Junior improved 20% or 6.11 centimeters.</li><li>This was accomplished in a 5 month period. They did one specific strength training session per week plus a series of exercises to be implemented during their regular gymnastics trainings.</li><li>We used a mix of squatting, deadlifting and pressing movements with a special emphasis on glutes and core. Plyometrics and jumping and landing technique were also part of the program.</li><li>A big percentage of the improvement can be attributed to two factors: One is the gymnasts still being in a growing phase (they are 13 to 15 years old). The other one is due to the fact that they had no previous history of strength training, which elicits a high initial response.</li></ul><p>Here’s a peek of how we trained:</p></div></div><div class="et_pb_module et_pb_video et_pb_video_0"><div class="et_pb_video_box"><div class="fluid-width-video-wrapper"><iframe id="fitvid0" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xpM0pqmNR9Q?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></div></div></div><div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_1 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left"><div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p><strong>Top 3 Jumpers:</strong></p><p><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/top3.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-24622" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/top3-300x171.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 370px) 100vw, 370px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/top3-300x171.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/top3-768x439.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/top3-610x349.jpg 610w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/top3.jpg 826w" alt="top3" width="370" height="211" /></a></p><p>When I see an athlete jumping high, my blood pressure raises.</p><p>Ever since I played sports myself, I put a lot of effort into improving my jumps and later the jumps of the athletes I have worked with.</p><p>By the end of January 2016, I started strength training Gloria Junior from PNV/Attitude clubs.</p><p>The focus of my intervention was<strong> increasing jump height</strong>, and that’s what we measured and trained for.</p><p>The benefits of getting stronger transfer to jumping, but also include enhancements in general sports skills as well as decreases in risk of injury (Suchomel, Nimphius, & Stone, 2016).</p><p>While jumping is only a very small part of success in gymnastics, it is still an important one.</p><p>Flexibility isn’t enough if power isn’t in place, as there won’t even be enough time to express the movement in the air and land safely.</p><p>Lately, I have been developing an interest in statistics and data analysis, so I decided to play with the numbers.</p><p>Please notice I am a beginner in this area.</p><p>For those interested, keep on reading (it gets a bit technical).</p><p>To develop jumps in a young gymnast, we need a combination of <strong>explosive movements and heavy-resistance strength training</strong> (Maffiuletti et al., 2016).</p><p>That’s what we did with Gloria Junior.</p><p>In the past, the times when I have failed to improve the jumping height of athletes, it’s been due to:</p><ul><li><strong>Lack of consistency</strong>. You can’t strength train 6 weeks, stop training, train another 6 weeks, stop again and expect to increase or even maintain jumping power. Strength and power need to be developed and maintained as high as possible year round.</li></ul><ul><li><strong>Poor Nutrition</strong>. <em>Fat </em>don’t<em> fly</em>. Any body mass that is not directly contributing to propulsive forces is actually hindering your power. Overweight gymnasts won’t jump high.</li></ul><p>No training system will overcome these 2 premises.</p><p>With Gloria Junior, I have had the opportunity to work for 5 months on a semi-consistent basis.</p><p>I wasn’t able to fit strength training as often as I would have liked, but we kept it fairly regular.</p><p>This eliminates <strong>constraint number one</strong> (lack of consistency).</p><p>When it comes to bodyweight, they are visibly lean. This eliminates <strong>the second constraint</strong> (sub-optimal fat levels).</p><p>This is a <strong>Jackpot</strong> for me.</p><p>Now I can really strength train them and help them get the results they want.</p><p>I decided to use <a href="http://www.complementarytraining.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mladen Janovic</a> approach to statistical analysis (a big influence of mine).</p><p>We tested a countermovement jump using a validated contact platform from Chronojump.</p><p>Here are the results of the test and the re-test:</p><p><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-24584" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo-300x297.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 525px) 100vw, 525px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo-300x297.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo-768x760.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo-610x604.jpg 610w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/goo.jpg 904w" alt="data1" width="525" height="520" /></a></p><p> </p></div></div><div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_2 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left"><div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p>To see the jump scores, look into the column that says <strong>“ABK (Cm)” in blue</strong>, and the column that says <strong>“ABK (Cm)” in yellow</strong> (test and re-test).</p><p>In the lower table, you can see the <strong>average score of the team </strong>(mean), the <strong>standard deviation </strong>(SD) and the <strong>best and worst jumps </strong>(Min and Max).</p><p>For averages, I <strong>didn’t take into account the athletes in red</strong>, as they missed one of the tests due to injury/sickness.</p><p>I have also included the <strong>z-scores</strong>, which is a measure that says how good each gymnast can jump compared to the average of the team.</p><p>A z-score <strong>above 0</strong> means you can jump more than the average, and a z-score <strong>under 0</strong> means you jump less than the team average.</p><p>While you could already see this directly from the jump height in centimeters, it is a very useful measure to deeper analyze the data. Keep reading.</p><p>Now, the next step was to visualize the improvements in <strong>absolute change</strong> (how many centimeters they improved) as well as in <strong>relative change</strong> (what percentage of improvement).</p><p>I also added each individual and mean z-scores.</p><p>You can see this on the 2 right columns:</p><p><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/ree.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-24585" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/ree-300x170.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 726px) 100vw, 726px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/ree-300x170.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/ree-768x435.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/ree-1024x580.jpg 1024w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/ree-610x346.jpg 610w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/ree-1080x612.jpg 1080w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/ree.jpg 1589w" alt="data2" width="726" height="412" /></a></p><p> </p></div></div><div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_3 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left"><div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p>Realize that weight loss or weight gain, having a bad day, wherein the menstrual cycle the athlete is, error in the measurement and many other factors <strong>all can affect test scores</strong> positively or negatively.</p><p>Results in tests are just an opportunity to see trends, not a definitive judgment in performance (leave that for competition time).</p><p>Let’s look now at correlations:</p><p><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/d.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-24587" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/d-300x97.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 492px) 100vw, 492px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/d-300x97.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/d-768x249.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/d-610x198.jpg 610w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/d.jpg 796w" alt="correlation" width="492" height="159" /></a></p><p>Looking at the table, we see almost no correlation between test and absolute and relative changes.</p><p>This means that <strong>both the gymnasts with high and low initial scores improved a lot</strong>.</p><p>This is a sign that they are still beginner athletes (in terms of strength).</p><p>As they become more advanced, it will be a lot harder to see improvements over time.</p><p>We should then see a negative correlation between jumping skill and magnitude of improvement.</p><p>To make the data easier to understand, we can create some simple <strong>data visualization</strong>.</p><p>One way to do it is using scatter plots, or points distributed along a vertical and/or horizontal axis.</p><p>Below is a scatter plot of the <strong>initial test </strong>and<strong> relative change </strong>or improvement.</p><p>The more on the left an athlete is, the less they jumped in the initial test.</p><p>The higher an athlete is, the more they improved in terms of percentage change.</p><p>I also added <strong>a trend line</strong>, which is showing a <strong>non-significant</strong> skew towards low initial test scores having a bigger relative change.</p><p><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/rr.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-24588" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/rr-300x149.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/rr-300x149.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/rr-768x380.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/rr-1024x507.jpg 1024w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/rr-610x302.jpg 610w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/rr-1080x535.jpg 1080w" alt="correlation2" width="608" height="302" /></a></p><p>Next one is a scatter plot of the <strong>relative change in z-scores-</strong>.</p><p>Here we can see who improved the most compared to the average of the team (0 in the vertical axis):</p><p><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/der.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-24589" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/der-300x182.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 604px) 100vw, 604px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/der-300x182.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/der-768x467.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/der-1024x622.jpg 1024w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/der-610x371.jpg 610w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/der-1080x656.jpg 1080w" alt="correlation3" width="604" height="366" /></a></p><p> </p></div></div><div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_4 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left"><div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p>Now this is where it gets interesting.</p><p>I divided the gymnasts into <strong>high and low responders. </strong></p><p>We can accomplish this by looking at the z-scores of the initial test and the relative change.</p><p>This way we end up with a very useful quadrant where we can rapidly see:</p><ul><li>Gymnasts with a <strong>low initial ability that responded poorly</strong> to the training program.</li><li>Gymnasts with a <strong>low initial ability that responded well</strong> to the training program.</li><li>Gymnasts with a <strong>high initial ability that responded poorly</strong> to the training program.</li><li>Gymnasts with a <strong>high initial ability that responded well</strong> to the training program.</li></ul><p><a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/quadrant.jpg"><img class="alignnone wp-image-24590" src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/quadrant-300x174.jpg" sizes="(max-width: 807px) 100vw, 807px" srcset="https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/quadrant-300x174.jpg 300w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/quadrant-768x445.jpg 768w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/quadrant-1024x593.jpg 1024w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/quadrant-610x353.jpg 610w, https://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/quadrant-1080x626.jpg 1080w" alt="quadrant" width="807" height="468" /></a></p><p>This is very cool because it will allow us to individualize the training a lot more, <strong>putting gymnasts into groups</strong> depending on their characteristics.</p><p>We need to change the training for some gymnasts while others can keep training in the same manner.</p><p>We also can decide <strong>how much strength training is necessary</strong> for each of them according to their individual response.</p><p>Maybe some gymnasts can focus on gymnastics skills and less in strength while others should focus on strength and less in skills.</p><p>Again, these are just trends and we have to be very careful when interpreting tests results.</p><p>But provided that we don’t make false conclusions, this is <strong>very valuable information</strong>.</p><p>With that said, I am confident in this approach.</p><p>Expect high-flying gymnasts next season.</p><p>Maffiuletti, N. A., Aagaard, P., Blazevich, A. J., Folland, J., Tillin, N., & Duchateau, J. (2016). Rate of force development: physiological and methodological considerations. <em>European Journal of Applied Physiology</em>, <em>116</em>(6), 1091–116. doi:10.1007/s00421-016-3346-6</p><p>Mladen Janovic. (n.d.). Complementary Training. Retrieved from www.complementarytraining.net</p><p>Suchomel, T. J., Nimphius, S., & Stone, M. H. (2016). The Importance of Muscular Strength in Athletic Performance. <em>Sports Medicine</em>, 1–31. doi:10.1007/s40279-016-0486-0</p></div></div>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_enable_shortcode_tracking]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_custom_css]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jetpack_related_posts_cache]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:32:"8f6677c9d6b0f903e98ad32ec61f8deb";a:2:{s:7:"expires";i:1532793789;s:7:"payload";a:3:{i:0;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29333;}i:1;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29355;}i:2;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28804;}}}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[et_enqueued_post_fonts]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:2:{s:6:"family";a:1:{s:21:"et-gf-source-sans-pro";s:100:"Source+Sans+Pro:200,200italic,300,300italic,regular,italic,600,600italic,700,700italic,900,900italic";}s:6:"subset";a:7:{i:0;s:8:"cyrillic";i:1;s:5:"greek";i:2;s:10:"vietnamese";i:3;s:5:"latin";i:4;s:9:"greek-ext";i:5;s:9:"latin-ext";i:6;s:12:"cyrillic-ext";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_thumbnail_id]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[29963]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_show_author_inthis_post]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[author_default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_builder_version]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BB|Divi|3.2.2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>5 IDEAS TO MAKE AGG MORE POPULAR</title>
		<link>https://entrena.fi/five-ideas/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 23:50:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://entrena.fi/?p=28800</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[et_pb_section bb_built="1" specialty="off" _builder_version="3.2.2"][et_pb_row _builder_version="3.0.96"][et_pb_column type="4_4"][et_pb_text admin_label="blog post model" max_width="560px" text_line_height_last_edited="on|phone" use_border_color="off" header_font_size="40px" text_font_size="16" text_line_height="1.6em" text_line_height_tablet="1.7em" header_text_color="#0c71c3" background_position="top_left" background_repeat="repeat" background_size="initial" _builder_version="3.2.2" text_font="Verdana||||||||" text_font_size_last_edited="on|phone" header_font_size_last_edited="on|desktop"]

In Finland, I often hear the word “Huippuvoimistelu.”

It means something like “professional gymnastics” or “elite gymnastics.”

If we look in Wikipedia the definition of pro sports, it says:
“Professional sports, as opposed to amateur sports, are sports in which athletes receive payment for their performance.”

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>No money</strong></h3>
To my knowledge, no AGG gymnast earns money.

Not even the winners of the world championships.

In fact, traveling, training and paying coaches costs the gymnasts -or more precisely, their families- a lot of money.

As much as it hurts me to admit, AGG is not a professional sport.

It doesn’t mean that it won’t be one day.

It just means that right now it’s not.

I will agree that anyone involved in AGG is not in it for getting rich, but it is somehow sad that well over a decade of training will only get you a medal worth 5 euros.

However, not all hope is lost.

What can we do to help clubs and gymnasts gain exposure and have better training conditions?

We need to think of different marketing strategies that don’t fit the old-school approach.

If someone would ask you who is the most famous gymnast in AGG, you probably couldn’t answer.

Every other sport has stars.

Why don’t we have stars? Where are the celebrity gymnasts?

You may not know much about bodybuilding.

But if you live in Finland, you know who Jari “Bull” Mentula is.

You may not like soccer, but you have heard about Messi and Ronaldo.

Every sport needs idols.

&nbsp;

<strong>Here are 5 ideas that you could use to grow AGG:</strong>

<strong>1.</strong> If you are a gymnast, open a website.

Write about gymnastics, write about the clothes you wear, what you eat, what music do you like.

Maybe soon everybody will know who you are and buy t-shirts with your name on them. You can be the first star of your sport.

<strong>2.</strong> If you’re an AGG Club, create a youtube series showing the joys and struggles of a group of gymnasts.

The average person can’t relate to the specifics of the sport, but they understand passion, drama, defeat, and joy.

<strong>3.</strong> If you are a coach, Create a daily program on Snapchat giving training tips for gymnasts.

Once the channel has thousands of followers, organize paid seminars around the country for both gymnasts and coaches.

<strong>4.</strong> If you’re the Federation, organize an AGG competition for the women’s category.

After covering costs (all teams pay inscriptions) use the rest of the money as a price for the top 3 teams.

Paying for results will increase the level of the sport very quickly.

<strong>5.</strong> If you’re a parent, have lots of patience

&nbsp;

We can complain that AGG is expensive for families and that coaches get lousy pay, but what are we doing to change it?

My small contribution is writing this blog.

What is yours?

[/et_pb_text][et_pb_social_media_follow follow_button="on" _builder_version="3.2.2" border_radii="on|100%|100%|100%|100%" saved_tabs="all" global_module="29607"][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="instagram" url="https://www.instagram.com/agg_entrena" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#517fa4" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on"]

&lt;p&gt;Instagram&lt;/p&gt;

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="facebook" url="https://www.facebook.com/entrenafi/" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#3b5998" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px" background_video_pause_outside_viewport="on" box_shadow_style="none"]

Facebook

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="youtube" url="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnr5AS5uScFE2hmcGBsJitA" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#a82400" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px"]

Youtube

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][/et_pb_social_media_follow][/et_pb_column][/et_pb_row][/et_pb_section]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[How you can contribute to make AGG more well-known]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>28800</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-03-12 01:50:34]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-03-11 23:50:34]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[five-ideas]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="other"><![CDATA[Other]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_monarch_override]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_color]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[#ffffff]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[light]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_show_title]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_post_hide_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_page_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[et_full_width_page]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_side_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[off]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_use_builder]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_ab_stats_refresh_interval]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hourly]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_old_content]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_0 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left"><div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p>There has been a lot of speculation since Katja Volkova announced that she is <a href="http://yle.fi/urheilu/3-9238223">quitting gymnastics</a> due to poor training conditions.<br />How is it possible that the best gymnast in the country doesn’t have a good place to train?<br />If young girls don’t have someone to look up to, how are they want to get into sports?<br />But I digress.<br />This article is not about rhythmic gymnastics, but about its little sister: AGG.<br />Often we hear the term “<strong>Huippuvoimistelu</strong>” in AGG conversations. Something like “professional gymnastics” or “elite gymnastics.”<br />By definition, the bests AGG teams in the world are “elite” in their sport.<br />However, it’s the “professional” part of the definition that I have trouble with.<br />If we look in Wikipedia the definition of pro sports, it says:<br /><strong>“<em>Professional sports, as opposed to amateur sports, are sports in which athletes receive payment for their performance.</em>”</strong><br />To my knowledge, no amount of money is given to the gymnasts that participate in national or international competitions, not even to the winners.<br />In fact, traveling, training and paying coaches costs the athletes a lot of money (or to their parents, to be more precise).<br />As much as it hurts us to admit, AGG is not a professional sport.<br />It doesn’t mean that it won’t be one day, it just means that right now it’s not and we can’t deny that.</p></div></div><div class="et_pb_module et_pb_image et_pb_image_0 et_animated et-waypoint et_always_center_on_mobile fade et-animated"><span class="et_pb_image_wrap"><img src="http://www.attitudesports.fi/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/medal-1622523.png" alt="" /></span></div><div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_1 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_center"><div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p><em>It’s not about the money, but years of training will only get you a medal worth 5 euros.</em></p></div></div><div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_2 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left"><div class="et_pb_text_inner"><p>Let’s look at Ice Hockey as an example.<br />Finnish people decided that they like Ice Hockey and that they were willing to pay to watch it in person and on TV.<br />As a lot of people are watching Hockey, sponsors think it is a good idea to pay the clubs and players to promote their brands.<br />So far, the world isn’t really interested in paying money to watch AGG.<br />Thus, why would companies want to pay AGG clubs big money for brand exposure?<br />AGG will never be ice hockey, <strong>but we can make it better</strong>.<br />What can we do to allow clubs and gymnasts gain exposure, have better training conditions and make money?<br />We need to think of different marketing strategies that don’t fit the old school (and expensive) approach.<br />If someone would ask you who is the most famous gymnast in AGG, <strong>you probably couldn’t answer</strong>.<br /><strong>Every other sport has stars.</strong><br />Why don’t we have stars? Where are the celebrity gymnasts?<br />You may not know much about bodybuilding but you know who “Bull” Mentula is.<br />You may not like soccer but you have heard about Messi and Ronaldo.<br />Every sport needs idols.</p><p>Here are 5 ideas that you can use today to help grow the sport you love:<br />• <strong>If you are a gymnast:</strong> open a website, write about gymnastics, write about the clothes you wear, what you eat, what music do you like. Maybe soon everybody will know who you are and buy t-shirts with your name on them. You can be the first star of your sport.<br />• <strong>If you’re an AGG Club:</strong> Make a youtube series about the struggles of a group of gymnasts. The average person can’t really relate to the specifics of the sport, but they understand passion, drama, defeat, and joy.<br />• <strong>If you are a coach:</strong> Create a daily program on Snapchat giving training tips for gymnasts. Once the channel has thousands of followers, organize paid seminars around the country for both gymnasts and coaches.<br />• <strong>If you’re the Federation:</strong> Organize an AGG competition for the women’s category. After covering costs (all teams pay inscriptions) use the rest of the money as a price for the top 3 teams. Paying for results will increase the level of the sport very quickly.<br />• <strong>If you’re a parent:</strong> Have lots of patience <img class="emoji" draggable="false" src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/svg/1f642.svg" alt="🙂" /></p><p>If you have other ideas that you think are good, please send them to me: sergio@entrena.fi.<br />Maybe together we can make the sport better.<br />We can complain that AGG is expensive for families and that coaches get bad pay, but what are we doing to change it?<br />My small contribution is writing this blog.<br />Yours can be sharing it so others may benefit.</p></div></div>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_enable_shortcode_tracking]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_custom_css]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jetpack_related_posts_cache]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:32:"8f6677c9d6b0f903e98ad32ec61f8deb";a:2:{s:7:"expires";i:1533502912;s:7:"payload";a:3:{i:0;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28790;}i:1;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29355;}i:2;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29257;}}}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_thumbnail_id]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[29972]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_show_author_inthis_post]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[author_default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_builder_version]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BB|Divi|3.2.2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[et_enqueued_post_fonts]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:2:{s:6:"family";a:1:{s:21:"et-gf-source-sans-pro";s:100:"Source+Sans+Pro:200,200italic,300,300italic,regular,italic,600,600italic,700,700italic,900,900italic";}s:6:"subset";a:7:{i:0;s:8:"cyrillic";i:1;s:5:"greek";i:2;s:10:"vietnamese";i:3;s:5:"latin";i:4;s:9:"greek-ext";i:5;s:9:"latin-ext";i:6;s:12:"cyrillic-ext";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_wp_old_slug]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[is-agg-really-a-professional-sport]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>3 REASONS WHY CHILDREN DOING GYMNASTICS SHOULD STRENGTH TRAIN</title>
		<link>https://entrena.fi/3-reasons-strength/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 23:51:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://entrena.fi/?p=28802</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[et_pb_section bb_built="1" specialty="off" _builder_version="3.2.2"][et_pb_row _builder_version="3.0.96"][et_pb_column type="4_4"][et_pb_text admin_label="blog post model" max_width="560px" text_line_height_last_edited="on|phone" use_border_color="off" header_font_size="40px" text_font_size="16" text_line_height="1.6em" text_line_height_tablet="1.7em" header_text_color="#0c71c3" background_position="top_left" background_repeat="repeat" background_size="initial" _builder_version="3.2.2" text_font="Verdana||||||||" text_font_size_last_edited="on|phone" header_font_size_last_edited="on|desktop"]

Why do gymnasts need dedicated strength training?

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Fewer injuries</strong></h3>
Gymnasts need a moderate amount of stress on their skeleton to build bone density.

Jumps are one part of it, weightlifting with perfect form is another.

Doing too much can be a bad thing, but gymnastics without a base of strength is trouble guaranteed.

The dose makes the poison, but such thing as a healthy, competitive gymnast can exist if treated with care.

The bottom line is this: don't wait to get hurt to start strength training.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Better movement quality</strong></h3>
You’ve seen articles pop up in the news about this: kids are fatter and more sedentary than ever.

The children from the 1970’s supposedly moved very well.

While I wasn’t there to confirm this, it’s true that millennials can’t even get into a deep squat position without falling on their face.

Start with learning how to pick up a weight off the floor with a flat back, followed by lunges and hip hinge variations.

If a gymnast can't master basic movement patterns, you can't expect them to do back extensions and pirouettes with impeccable form.

Good movement needs to be the only movement allowed, starting from the basics at an early age.

Sounds easy, but no one does it.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Health and lifestyle</strong></h3>
The benefits of having a positive early experience with strength training go far beyond gymnastics.

The competitive life of a gymnast lasts the blink of an eye, and you want to keep on working out after that.

When gymnastics ends, many girls can’t find joy in regular exercise.

This leads to problems managing their health and their weight because of lack of habit or motivation.

Building good manners in the gym and a taste for general exercise can prevent this problem.

Make gym training an enjoyable experience and it's benefits will carry on for decades.

&nbsp;

If you liked the article, please share so others may benefit.

[/et_pb_text][et_pb_social_media_follow follow_button="on" _builder_version="3.2.2" border_radii="on|100%|100%|100%|100%" saved_tabs="all" global_module="29607"][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="instagram" url="https://www.instagram.com/agg_entrena" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#517fa4" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on"]

&lt;p&gt;Instagram&lt;/p&gt;

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="facebook" url="https://www.facebook.com/entrenafi/" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#3b5998" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px" background_video_pause_outside_viewport="on" box_shadow_style="none"]

Facebook

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="youtube" url="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnr5AS5uScFE2hmcGBsJitA" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#a82400" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px"]

Youtube

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][/et_pb_social_media_follow][/et_pb_column][/et_pb_row][/et_pb_section]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Getting stronger isn't just for winning competitions.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>28802</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-03-12 01:51:13]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-03-11 23:51:13]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[3-reasons-strength]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="strength"><![CDATA[Strength]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="injuries"><![CDATA[Injuries]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_monarch_override]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_color]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[#ffffff]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[light]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_show_title]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_post_hide_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_page_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[et_full_width_page]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_side_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[off]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_use_builder]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_ab_stats_refresh_interval]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hourly]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_old_content]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<p>The AGG revolution has started.</p><p>Coaches and parents have woken up. The doubters remain in denial, while strength training is spreading quicker than the Macarena.</p><p>The stigma surrounding gymnastics and weight training is alive and well. We are all humans, and common sense is not very common, so education is the key.</p><p>Attitude Sports understood long ago that there is a better way, as this was the sole reason for its creation. In an ever changing world, not taking risks is risky. Minorit is the revolution inside the revolution, and they have made a safe bet.</p><p>I am going to take care of their physical development, and here’s how I’m going about it:</p><p><strong>LESS INJURIES</strong><br />Children need a moderate amount of stress on their skeleton to build bone density. Jumps are one part of it, weight lifting with perfect form is another. Doing too much can be a bad thing, but gymnastics without a base of strength is trouble guaranteed. The dose makes the poison, but such thing as a healthy, competitive gymnast can exist if treated with care.</p><p>Weight lifting is safe: I have only had two athletes hurt in 10 years of trainings, in both cases due to inadequate training equipment. Lesson learned, and next decade I’m lowering that track record from two to zero.</p><p><strong>MAKE THE BASICS GREAT AGAIN</strong><br />You’ve seen articles pop up in the news about this: Finnish kids are fatter and more sedentary than ever. The children from the 1970’s supposedly moved very well. While I wasn’t there to confirm this, it’s true that Millennials can’t even get into a deep squat position without falling.</p><p>With Minorit, I am not going to let that happen: Starting with learning how to pick up a weight off the floor with a flat back, to mastering lunges and hip hinge variations, good movement will be the only movement allowed. Sounds easy, but no one does it.</p><p>Below are a few videos from our first ever training session. While there are a dozen things to work on, long-term view prevails.</p><div class="fluid-width-video-wrapper"><iframe id="fitvid0" class="youtube-player" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fqhD-MnV1xA?version=3&rel=1&fs=1&autohide=2&showsearch=0&showinfo=1&iv_load_policy=1&wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></div><p><strong>TRAINING LIKE IT’S 2017</strong><br />AGG is a traditional sport, and there’s a lot of imitation. Surprisingly, tradition in gymnastics doesn’t include learning the basic movement skills. While experience is invaluable and what works should not be changed, there’s a place for improvement.</p><p>The Russian training model is great if you have 100000 gymnasts to choose from, but a science-based approach is more appropriate for the Finnish context. People saying “It has always been done this way” have done more damage throughout history than those embracing change.</p><p><strong>A PLAN THAT WORKS FOR YOU</strong><br />I run away from glorified textbooks that suggest a standardized plan for youth sports. They look good in PowerPoint presentations, but each gymnast is different and chronological age is not the same as biological.</p><p>Luckily, training in small groups will allow me to adjust load and intensity individually instead of having everyone doing the same.</p><p>Cookie-cutter approaches are a curse for the sport and should be a thing of the past. Money is always an issue, but investing in the best training is cheaper than the worst doctor.</p><div class="fluid-width-video-wrapper"><iframe id="fitvid1" class="youtube-player" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/U6NwREsz1ok?version=3&rel=1&fs=1&autohide=2&showsearch=0&showinfo=1&iv_load_policy=1&wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></div><p><strong>MORE THAN GYMNASTICS</strong><br />The benefits of having a positive early experience with strength training go far beyond gymnastics. Most coaches are failed athletes, and we all have an ego: I am selfishly proud of how Gloria Nova<a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/2016/06/10/the-secrets-of-jumping/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong> increased their jump height 20% in 5 months</strong></a>.</p><p>However, as I get older, I realize that the potential advantage of acquiring a taste for general exercise is bigger than medals. The competitive life of a gymnast lasts the blink of an eye, and you want to keep on working out after that.</p><p>When gymnastics ends, many girls can’t find joy in regular exercise, struggling with problems to manage their health because of lack of habit or no interest.</p><p><strong>A UNIQUE CASE</strong><br />You won’t find a lot of AGG teams doing strength training, especially not the right kind. Minorit is the exception: For the first time, a team is starting early enough (12-13 years old) to reap the full benefits of postural control, power development, and foundational movements.</p><p>Slow progress is a must, but we can’t just do pushups and planks and expect a gymnast’s body to handle thousands of jumps a week without stress fractures.</p><p>Regarding performance, strength won’t magically make a champion, but it will allow those that are good to express their skills better. We should think of A.G.G as a puzzle, where if one piece is not in place, you never get to enjoy the full picture that makes a good gymnast.</p><p>The strength piece is typically missing, but Minorit is about to glue it together.</p><p>Here are Vilina and Iris, who recently joined the squad:</p><div class="fluid-width-video-wrapper"><iframe id="fitvid2" class="youtube-player" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Q83Ovhfv268?version=3&rel=1&fs=1&autohide=2&showsearch=0&showinfo=1&iv_load_policy=1&wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></div><p>Is Minorit the future of A.G.G? Find out by staying updated about their journey <strong><a href="http://www.instagram.com/entrena_" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a> </strong>and<strong><a href="http://www.facebook.com/entrenafi"> here</a>.</strong></p><p>If you would like to see stronger healthier gymnasts, please share this post so others may benefit.</p>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_enable_shortcode_tracking]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_custom_css]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jetpack_related_posts_cache]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:32:"8f6677c9d6b0f903e98ad32ec61f8deb";a:2:{s:7:"expires";i:1533884168;s:7:"payload";a:3:{i:0;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29355;}i:1;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28790;}i:2;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28796;}}}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_thumbnail_id]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[29974]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_show_author_inthis_post]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[author_default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_builder_version]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BB|Divi|3.2.2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[et_enqueued_post_fonts]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:2:{s:6:"family";a:1:{s:21:"et-gf-source-sans-pro";s:100:"Source+Sans+Pro:200,200italic,300,300italic,regular,italic,600,600italic,700,700italic,900,900italic";}s:6:"subset";a:7:{i:0;s:8:"cyrillic";i:1;s:5:"greek";i:2;s:10:"vietnamese";i:3;s:5:"latin";i:4;s:9:"greek-ext";i:5;s:9:"latin-ext";i:6;s:12:"cyrillic-ext";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_wp_old_slug]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[minorit-breakthrough]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>HOW TO JUMP SKY HIGH</title>
		<link>https://entrena.fi/jump-high/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 23:51:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://entrena.fi/?p=28804</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[et_pb_section bb_built="1" specialty="off" _builder_version="3.2.2"][et_pb_row _builder_version="3.0.96"][et_pb_column type="4_4"][et_pb_text admin_label="blog post model" max_width="560px" text_line_height_last_edited="on|phone" use_border_color="off" header_font_size="40px" text_font_size="16" text_line_height="1.6em" text_line_height_tablet="1.7em" header_text_color="#0c71c3" background_position="top_left" background_repeat="repeat" background_size="initial" _builder_version="3.2.2" text_font="Verdana||||||||" text_font_size_last_edited="on|phone" header_font_size_last_edited="on|desktop"]

<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zG2xacpKX-A" width="1663" height="685" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe>

Most people make it way too complicated, but it is straightforward.

Below are the 3 things that will help gymnasts jump higher.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Lose extra weight</strong></h3>
Parents are worried about girls eating too little and ending up anorexic.

However, at least in Finland, the problem usually is that girls are overweight for AGG.

Not overweight for the average girl off the street.

I said overweight for AGG.

A sport that even has the word "aesthetic" in the name and that gets more and more competitive every year.

The problem is too much fat (dead weight) and too little muscle (useful for force production).

If you need to lose some body fat, do it the painful way: SLOWLY.

If you want to perform like an athlete, you must eat like an athlete.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Put more force into the ground</strong></h3>
The easiest way to do this is by improving your maximal and sub-maximal strength inside the gym.

Notice that a year or two of serious training is a minimum time to do this.

If you try to do this on your own, you will end up injured or overtrained.

Get an experienced coach that can show you the basics of strength training.

It will be money well invested.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Put force into the ground quicker</strong></h3>
If you already are strong, you may not need to spend much time lifting heavy.

Instead, you can spend more time doing plyometrics (jumps with a short stretch-shortening cycle) and lifting in “speed-strength” velocities, where the load on the barbell is between 30% and 60% of your one repetition maximum.

If you are lifting with light loads, move the barbell as quickly as possible on the way up as if you were to take off like a rocket.

If you are training plyometrics, keep the stretch-shortening cycle as quick as possible.

This type of training will improve your ability to produce high forces in a short amount of time.

&nbsp;

You will hear a lot of nonsense about different ways to increase your vertical jump.

However, it comes down to simple physics.

Get fit, get stronger, and put your strength on the ground quicker.

Nothing else will give you results.

&nbsp;

[/et_pb_text][et_pb_social_media_follow follow_button="on" _builder_version="3.2.2" border_radii="on|100%|100%|100%|100%" saved_tabs="all" global_module="29607"][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="instagram" url="https://www.instagram.com/agg_entrena" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#517fa4" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on"]

&lt;p&gt;Instagram&lt;/p&gt;

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="facebook" url="https://www.facebook.com/entrenafi/" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#3b5998" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px" background_video_pause_outside_viewport="on" box_shadow_style="none"]

Facebook

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="youtube" url="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnr5AS5uScFE2hmcGBsJitA" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#a82400" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px"]

Youtube

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][/et_pb_social_media_follow][/et_pb_column][/et_pb_row][/et_pb_section]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[3 things you need to do to jump very high.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>28804</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-03-12 01:51:49]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-03-11 23:51:49]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[jump-high]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_format" nicename="post-format-link"><![CDATA[Link]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="strength"><![CDATA[Strength]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="jumps"><![CDATA[Jumps]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_monarch_override]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_color]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[#ffffff]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[light]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_show_title]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_post_hide_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_page_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[et_full_width_page]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_side_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[off]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_use_builder]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_ab_stats_refresh_interval]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hourly]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_old_content]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<a href="http://www.attitudesports.fi/2017/01/21/agg-worlds-2017-jumping-for-gold/">http://www.attitudesports.fi/2017/01/21/agg-worlds-2017-jumping-for-gold/</a>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_enable_shortcode_tracking]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_custom_css]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jetpack_related_posts_cache]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:32:"8f6677c9d6b0f903e98ad32ec61f8deb";a:2:{s:7:"expires";i:1532490092;s:7:"payload";a:3:{i:0;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28796;}i:1;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28790;}i:2;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29355;}}}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_thumbnail_id]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[30059]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_show_author_inthis_post]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[author_default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_builder_version]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BB|Divi|3.2.2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[et_enqueued_post_fonts]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:2:{s:6:"family";a:1:{s:21:"et-gf-source-sans-pro";s:100:"Source+Sans+Pro:200,200italic,300,300italic,regular,italic,600,600italic,700,700italic,900,900italic";}s:6:"subset";a:7:{i:0;s:8:"cyrillic";i:1;s:5:"greek";i:2;s:10:"vietnamese";i:3;s:5:"latin";i:4;s:9:"greek-ext";i:5;s:9:"latin-ext";i:6;s:12:"cyrillic-ext";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_wp_old_slug]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[jumping-for-gold]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>GYMNASTICS AND BIG MUSCLES</title>
		<link>https://entrena.fi/gymnastics-and-big-muscles/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 10:33:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://entrena.fi/?p=28952</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[et_pb_section bb_built="1" specialty="off" _builder_version="3.2.2"][et_pb_row _builder_version="3.0.96"][et_pb_column type="4_4"][et_pb_text admin_label="blog post model" max_width="560px" text_line_height_last_edited="on|phone" use_border_color="off" header_font_size="40px" text_font_size="16" text_line_height="1.6em" text_line_height_tablet="1.7em" header_text_color="#0c71c3" background_position="top_left" background_repeat="repeat" background_size="initial" _builder_version="3.2.2" text_font="Verdana||||||||" text_font_size_last_edited="on|phone" header_font_size_last_edited="on|desktop"]

During the last 2 and a half years I have talked a lot with A.G.G. coaches.

There are a few reasons that, in some cases, prevent them from embracing strength training as a part of their planning.

The biggest objection is the fear of growing big muscles, or the gymnasts appearing "too bulky."

It is no wonder that many still hold this belief.

There is no specific A.G.G. strength training education where the basics of physiology are studied in depth by the coaches.

This way, opinions are susceptive to be influenced by any outside input regardless of its scientific base, or the lack of it.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Are they going to get big?</strong></h3>
The amount of muscle an athlete can put is going to be mainly dictated by their genetics.

I train gymnasts that look athletic and others that look "skinny," both following very similar training programs.

A little perspective is needed.

The potential for most women to grow muscle is very limited.

Chances that a gymnast lifting weights once or twice a week will put a significant amount of muscle are very slim.

If it were that easy, you wouldn't have gyms full of young guys failing to grow big biceps year after year no matter how hard they try.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Bodyweight training vs. lifting weights</strong></h3>
Often, the perception of barbells and dumbbells is thought of as something too heavy for a gymnast, or just unnecessary.

Let's think about that for a second: gymnasts are absorbing several times their body weight every time they land on the ground after a jump.

Their bodies need to be prepared to handle landings and display excellent postural control.

Otherwise, the lower back, hips, knees, and ankles will be in for a very unpleasant ride.

Let's not lose sight the goal: decrease injury rate and improve performance.

You can develop strength with many different tools: Surely one of them is bodyweight-only training.

But it's not enough.

Bands, dumbbells, kettlebells, barbells are all valid and recommended.

Think of it of tools in a toolbox: The tools are a means to an end, not the end itself.

Don't be afraid of lifting weights.

Look for a coach with experience and start getting the results you've been dreaming about.

[/et_pb_text][et_pb_social_media_follow follow_button="on" _builder_version="3.2.2" border_radii="on|100%|100%|100%|100%" saved_tabs="all" global_module="29607"][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="instagram" url="https://www.instagram.com/agg_entrena" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#517fa4" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on"]

&lt;p&gt;Instagram&lt;/p&gt;

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="facebook" url="https://www.facebook.com/entrenafi/" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#3b5998" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px" background_video_pause_outside_viewport="on" box_shadow_style="none"]

Facebook

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="youtube" url="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnr5AS5uScFE2hmcGBsJitA" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#a82400" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px"]

Youtube

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][/et_pb_social_media_follow][/et_pb_column][/et_pb_row][/et_pb_section]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Why you shouldn't be worried about gymnasts putting on muscle.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>28952</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-03-28 13:33:41]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-03-28 10:33:41]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[gymnastics-and-big-muscles]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="other"><![CDATA[Other]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_monarch_override]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_color]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[#ffffff]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[light]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_show_title]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_post_hide_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_page_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[et_full_width_page]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_side_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[off]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_use_builder]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_ab_stats_refresh_interval]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hourly]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_old_content]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_enable_shortcode_tracking]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_custom_css]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jetpack_related_posts_cache]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:32:"8f6677c9d6b0f903e98ad32ec61f8deb";a:2:{s:7:"expires";i:1533590835;s:7:"payload";a:3:{i:0;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28792;}i:1;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29355;}i:2;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28790;}}}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[et_enqueued_post_fonts]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:2:{s:6:"family";a:1:{s:21:"et-gf-source-sans-pro";s:100:"Source+Sans+Pro:200,200italic,300,300italic,regular,italic,600,600italic,700,700italic,900,900italic";}s:6:"subset";a:7:{i:0;s:8:"cyrillic";i:1;s:5:"greek";i:2;s:10:"vietnamese";i:3;s:5:"latin";i:4;s:9:"greek-ext";i:5;s:9:"latin-ext";i:6;s:12:"cyrillic-ext";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_show_author_inthis_post]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[author_default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_builder_version]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BB|Divi|3.2.2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_thumbnail_id]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[29984]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>A LOOK AT THE DATA OF THE AGG WORLD CHAMPIONSHIPS</title>
		<link>https://entrena.fi/a-look-at-the-world-championships/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 10:44:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://entrena.fi/?p=29236</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[et_pb_section bb_built="1" specialty="off" _builder_version="3.2.2"][et_pb_row _builder_version="3.0.96"][et_pb_column type="4_4"][et_pb_text admin_label="blog post model" max_width="560px" text_line_height_last_edited="on|phone" use_border_color="off" header_font_size="40px" text_font_size="16" text_line_height="1.6em" text_line_height_tablet="1.7em" header_text_color="#0c71c3" background_position="top_left" background_repeat="repeat" background_size="initial" _builder_version="3.2.2" text_font="Verdana||||||||" text_font_size_last_edited="on|phone" header_font_size_last_edited="on|desktop"]

As the Helsinki 2017 world championship approaches, I want to analyze historical data about past competitions to get a closer picture of the event.

For a couple of months, I tried to find data regarding junior and women’s categories, all placings and points from every year, club, and country.

I contacted several AGG sources asking if such database is available, but luck wasn’t on my side.

I did find, however, the first three women’s placings of most years in the AGG federation website.

Please beware that I ignore if the data is 100% correct or not.

Also, If you see that I made any mistake with the analysis, just let me know, and I will correct it.

I put together a map and a simple table.

You will see it better on your desktop computer than on your phone:

<iframe src="https://app.powerbi.com/view?r=eyJrIjoiODMzN2Q2OWItMTljZi00YTk2LWFiMGItNDQ3ZWQ3NzFjOWFmIiwidCI6ImUwYWQ2MTUxLThmZTYtNGExNS05YjM0LTg0MzhiY2ZjZmYwMyIsImMiOjh9" width="933" height="350" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe>

First of all, click the double arrow on the bottom right corner to make it full screen.

On the first page, you can see where the event took place every year.

If you choose a particular year on the selector to the left, the map will show the place where the competition was held that year.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Insights</strong></h3>
<ul>
 	<li style="text-align: left;">Finland has previously held this competition 3 times: Helsinki 2000, Tampere 2006 and Lahti 2013.</li>
 	<li style="text-align: left;">No country has held the event more times than Finland.</li>
 	<li style="text-align: left;">Only one time has the competition been celebrated overseas: In 2008 in Toronto, Canada.</li>
</ul>
Now click on the second page where you can see the full dataset:
<ul>
 	<li>Finland has more golds than all the other gold medal countries combined, with a total of 9. Russia has 6 and Estonia 2. These are the only 3 countries to ever win a gold medal.</li>
 	<li>Russia has the most medals overall, with 19. Finland has 16, Bulgaria 9 and Estonia 8. Only these 4 countries have won a medal of any kind.</li>
 	<li>Russia has the longest winning streak of the competition with team Madonna: 4 consecutive golds, from 2011 to 2014.</li>
</ul>
Although A.G.G. is expanding in other areas of the world, it remains a sport dominated by Northern and Eastern-European countries.

Next month in Helsinki we have the chance to watch the best of the best.

If you live in Helsinki, don’t miss out: it may take another 17 years before the World Championship comes back to the city!

[/et_pb_text][et_pb_social_media_follow follow_button="on" _builder_version="3.2.2" border_radii="on|100%|100%|100%|100%" saved_tabs="all" global_module="29607"][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="instagram" url="https://www.instagram.com/agg_entrena" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#517fa4" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on"]

&lt;p&gt;Instagram&lt;/p&gt;

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="facebook" url="https://www.facebook.com/entrenafi/" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#3b5998" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px" background_video_pause_outside_viewport="on" box_shadow_style="none"]

Facebook

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="youtube" url="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnr5AS5uScFE2hmcGBsJitA" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#a82400" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px"]

Youtube

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][/et_pb_social_media_follow][/et_pb_column][/et_pb_row][/et_pb_section]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[A closer look at the history of the World Championships.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>29236</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-04-21 13:44:02]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-04-21 10:44:02]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[a-look-at-the-world-championships]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="other"><![CDATA[Other]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_monarch_override]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_color]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[#ffffff]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[light]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_show_title]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_post_hide_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_page_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[et_full_width_page]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_side_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[off]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_use_builder]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_ab_stats_refresh_interval]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hourly]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_old_content]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[<p>As the Helsinki 2017 world championship approaches (get your ticket!), I thought it would be cool to analyze historical data about past competitions to get a closer picture of the event.</p><p>For a couple of months, I tried to find data regarding junior and women’s categories, all placings and points from every year, club, and country.<br />I contacted several AGG sources asking if such database is available, but luck wasn’t on my side.</p><p>I did find, however, the first three women’s placings of most years in the <a href="http://www.ifagg.com/competition/world-championships/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">AGG federation site</a> and in an <a href="http://gymner.com/node/57847" target="_blank" rel="noopener">anonym blog post</a>. Please beware that I ignore if the data is 100% correct or not. Also, If you see that I made any mistake with the analysis, just let me know and I will correct it.</p><p>I put together a map and a simple table (better if you are on your desktop computer than on your phone):</p><p><iframe src="https://app.powerbi.com/view?r=eyJrIjoiODMzN2Q2OWItMTljZi00YTk2LWFiMGItNDQ3ZWQ3NzFjOWFmIiwidCI6ImUwYWQ2MTUxLThmZTYtNGExNS05YjM0LTg0MzhiY2ZjZmYwMyIsImMiOjh9" width="933" height="350" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></p><p>First of all, <strong>click the double arrow on the bottom right corner to make it full screen</strong>. In the first page, you can see where the event took place every year. If you choose a particular year on the selector to the left, the map will show the place where the competition was held that year.</p><p><strong>Insights:</strong><br />– Finland has previously held this competition 3 times. The first ever world championship in Helsinki 2000, Tampere 2006 and Lahti 2013.<br />– No country has held the event more times than Finland.<br />– Only one time has the competition been celebrated overseas: In 2008 in Toronto, Canada.</p><p><strong>In the second page, you can see the full dataset:</strong><br />– Finland has more golds than all the other gold medal countries combined, with a total of 9. Russia has 6 golds and Estonia 2. Only these 3 countries have ever won a gold medal.<br />– Russia has the most medals overall, with 19. Finland has a total of 16, Bulgaria 9 and Estonia 8. Only these 4 countries have won a medal of any kind.<br />– Russia has the longest winning streak of the competition with team Madonna. They won 4 consecutive golds, from 2011 to 2014.</p><p>Although A.G.G. is expanding in other areas of the world, it remains a sport dominated by Northern and Eastern-European countries.<br />Next month in Helsinki we have the chance to watch the best of the best. If you live in Helsinki, don’t miss out: It may take another 17 years before the World Championship comes back to the city.</p>]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_enable_shortcode_tracking]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_custom_css]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jetpack_related_posts_cache]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:32:"8f6677c9d6b0f903e98ad32ec61f8deb";a:2:{s:7:"expires";i:1533954292;s:7:"payload";a:3:{i:0;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28800;}i:1;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29257;}i:2;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29355;}}}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[et_enqueued_post_fonts]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:2:{s:6:"family";a:1:{s:21:"et-gf-source-sans-pro";s:100:"Source+Sans+Pro:200,200italic,300,300italic,regular,italic,600,600italic,700,700italic,900,900italic";}s:6:"subset";a:7:{i:0;s:8:"cyrillic";i:1;s:5:"greek";i:2;s:10:"vietnamese";i:3;s:5:"latin";i:4;s:9:"greek-ext";i:5;s:9:"latin-ext";i:6;s:12:"cyrillic-ext";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_show_author_inthis_post]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[author_default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_builder_version]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BB|Divi|3.2.2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_thumbnail_id]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[29978]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>READ ALL STUDIES EVER DONE ON AGG</title>
		<link>https://entrena.fi/read-all-studies-ever-done-on-agg/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2017 00:22:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://entrena.fi/?p=29241</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[et_pb_section bb_built="1" specialty="off" _builder_version="3.2.2"][et_pb_row _builder_version="3.0.96"][et_pb_column type="4_4"][et_pb_text admin_label="blog post model" max_width="560px" text_line_height_last_edited="on|phone" use_border_color="off" header_font_size="40px" text_font_size="16" text_line_height="1.6em" text_line_height_tablet="1.7em" header_text_color="#0c71c3" background_position="top_left" background_repeat="repeat" background_size="initial" _builder_version="3.2.2" text_font="Verdana||||||||" text_font_size_last_edited="on|phone" header_font_size_last_edited="on|desktop"]

For a couple of years, I have been looking for scientific literature on Aesthetic Group Gymnastics.

I feel that still today, a lot of the training is culture driven and not so much evidence-based.

Very few research has been done directly on AGG, but there are some interesting studies.

At the end of this article, there is a link that will give you access to all AGG-related studies that I have been able to find.

If you have any other studies, please send them to me, and I will update the folder.

Notice that as AGG research is limited: many of the studies are from rhythmic gymnastics or just simple articles.

Carefully analyzing the AGG-related studies has been of great help to me, so I am happy if it can be useful to you too.

Trading wild Friday nights out for reading research at home on AGG maximal oxygen consumption and low back injury incidence is not for everyone.

However, if you want to be the best in the sport, you need more than part-time dedication.

Enjoy: <a href="https://1drv.ms/f/s!Agp0f-omZkb0gs9wL5ChmEcyFMCYJQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">AGG STUDIES</a>

[/et_pb_text][et_pb_social_media_follow follow_button="on" _builder_version="3.2.2" border_radii="on|100%|100%|100%|100%" saved_tabs="all" global_module="29607"][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="instagram" url="https://www.instagram.com/agg_entrena" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#517fa4" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on"]

&lt;p&gt;Instagram&lt;/p&gt;

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="facebook" url="https://www.facebook.com/entrenafi/" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#3b5998" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px" background_video_pause_outside_viewport="on" box_shadow_style="none"]

Facebook

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="youtube" url="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnr5AS5uScFE2hmcGBsJitA" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#a82400" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px"]

Youtube

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][/et_pb_social_media_follow][/et_pb_column][/et_pb_row][/et_pb_section]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Get access to the full AGG scientific literature.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>29241</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-04-26 03:22:04]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-04-26 00:22:04]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[read-all-studies-ever-done-on-agg]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="other"><![CDATA[Other]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_monarch_override]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_color]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[#ffffff]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[light]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_show_title]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_post_hide_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_page_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[et_full_width_page]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_side_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[off]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_use_builder]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_ab_stats_refresh_interval]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hourly]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_old_content]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_enable_shortcode_tracking]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_custom_css]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jetpack_related_posts_cache]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:32:"8f6677c9d6b0f903e98ad32ec61f8deb";a:2:{s:7:"expires";i:1533102946;s:7:"payload";a:3:{i:0;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28790;}i:1;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29355;}i:2;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28800;}}}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[et_enqueued_post_fonts]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:2:{s:6:"family";a:1:{s:21:"et-gf-source-sans-pro";s:100:"Source+Sans+Pro:200,200italic,300,300italic,regular,italic,600,600italic,700,700italic,900,900italic";}s:6:"subset";a:7:{i:0;s:8:"cyrillic";i:1;s:5:"greek";i:2;s:10:"vietnamese";i:3;s:5:"latin";i:4;s:9:"greek-ext";i:5;s:9:"latin-ext";i:6;s:12:"cyrillic-ext";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_show_author_inthis_post]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[author_default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_builder_version]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BB|Divi|3.2.2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_thumbnail_id]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[29985]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>REVIEW OF THE 2017 HELSINKI WORLD CHAMPIONSHIPS</title>
		<link>https://entrena.fi/agg-helsinki/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 13:36:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://entrena.fi/?p=29257</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[et_pb_section bb_built="1" specialty="off" _builder_version="3.2.2"][et_pb_row _builder_version="3.0.96"][et_pb_column type="4_4"][et_pb_text admin_label="blog post model" max_width="560px" text_line_height_last_edited="on|phone" use_border_color="off" header_font_size="40px" text_font_size="16" text_line_height="1.6em" text_line_height_tablet="1.7em" header_text_color="#0c71c3" background_position="top_left" background_repeat="repeat" background_size="initial" _builder_version="3.2.2" text_font="Verdana||||||||" text_font_size_last_edited="on|phone" header_font_size_last_edited="on|desktop"]

<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UZb3WNuso4A" width="1663" height="734" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe>
<div class="et_pb_module et_pb_text et_pb_text_0 et_pb_bg_layout_light et_pb_text_align_left">
<div class="et_pb_text_inner">

&nbsp;

Everyone was saying that the 2017 Helsinki world championships was going to a unique event.

And they were right: It was a blast, and to hear that many people roaring in an AGG competition is something that no one that stepped into the carpet will forget.

If mainstream media cares about gymnastics or not is irrelevant: this is the era of the internet, and each of us is a media company.

We can reach a lot of people if the content is right: let's do it on our own.

My thing is AGG physical preparation only, so take my views on team performances with a grain of salt.

However, as a spectator, here are my 2 cents on the leading teams:

&nbsp;

<strong>Team Japan</strong> shined bright.

Many argue that they deserved a medal.

Everyone in Finland seems to like them, and honestly, what's there not to like? They don't try to be different: they ARE different.

Their choreography feels fresh and entertaining in a sport where it's hard to judge who's the best team.

They will smile at you in the halls and say "thank you" for no reason, but don't get fooled: they don't come for tourism, they compete to win to rip a medal off your neck as soon as they can.

&nbsp;

For <strong>Minetit</strong>, competing to be the world's best is just another day in the office.

Their Junior team is a legion of clones, and they will appear in your dreams if you try to beat them.

No one can take anything away from them: Their seniors pulled off a challenging music and made Finland proud.

Ultimately, they executed, and they got what matters the most: results.

2 Golds and their legend grows. Congrats Minetit.

&nbsp;

<strong>OVO</strong> is an AGG juggernaut.

The most successful club in the history of the sport is also the most professional: they are smart enough to take good care of their gymnasts, and they seem to have an army of coaches, osteopaths, and physiotherapists.

While they didn't sweep everybody else, they still delivered a majestic performance.

They are too big to not return to the highest spot on the podium sooner than later.

&nbsp;

<strong>Expressia</strong> was flawless. Or almost.

When someone misses glory by such a small difference, the silver does not taste as good.

Russian teams tend to be classic with their style, and at times I feel like I am watching rhythmic gymnastics.

However, their athletes are born for this: their legs will reach the sky, and their hips and ankles will bend freely and execute impeccably.

I want AGG to grow, but if Russia would make this sport a priority, the rest of the world wouldn't even be in the same league.

&nbsp;

Personally, I have to be very satisfied with my team, <strong>Gloria Jr</strong>.

We were able to progressively switch to a winner mindset, stay injury-free and give bigger clubs a run for their money.

All while remaining focused on our goals.

We will give our best effort to keep climbing the rankings.

Overall, what's exciting to me is that the most competitive side of this sport is still in its infancy.

Maybe, in a not so far away and not so impossible future, we could see a sold-out Helsinki Olympic Stadium cheering for teenage gymnasts in a World Championship.

Don't think I'm crazy: <strong>dreams come true if you work hard enough.</strong>

</div>
</div>
[/et_pb_text][et_pb_social_media_follow follow_button="on" _builder_version="3.2.2" border_radii="on|100%|100%|100%|100%" saved_tabs="all" global_module="29607"][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="instagram" url="https://www.instagram.com/agg_entrena" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#517fa4" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on"]

&lt;p&gt;Instagram&lt;/p&gt;

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="facebook" url="https://www.facebook.com/entrenafi/" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#3b5998" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px" background_video_pause_outside_viewport="on" box_shadow_style="none"]

Facebook

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="youtube" url="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnr5AS5uScFE2hmcGBsJitA" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#a82400" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px"]

Youtube

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][/et_pb_social_media_follow][/et_pb_column][/et_pb_row][/et_pb_section]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[A memorable event that will be remembered for years to come.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>29257</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-06-02 16:36:13]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-06-02 13:36:13]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[agg-helsinki]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="other"><![CDATA[Other]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_monarch_override]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_color]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[#ffffff]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[light]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_show_title]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_post_hide_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_page_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[et_full_width_page]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_side_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[off]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_use_builder]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_ab_stats_refresh_interval]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hourly]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_old_content]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_enable_shortcode_tracking]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_custom_css]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_wp_old_slug]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[world-championships-notes]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jetpack_related_posts_cache]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:32:"8f6677c9d6b0f903e98ad32ec61f8deb";a:2:{s:7:"expires";i:1533523165;s:7:"payload";a:3:{i:0;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29236;}i:1;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28800;}i:2;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29355;}}}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[et_enqueued_post_fonts]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:2:{s:6:"family";a:1:{s:21:"et-gf-source-sans-pro";s:100:"Source+Sans+Pro:200,200italic,300,300italic,regular,italic,600,600italic,700,700italic,900,900italic";}s:6:"subset";a:7:{i:0;s:8:"cyrillic";i:1;s:5:"greek";i:2;s:10:"vietnamese";i:3;s:5:"latin";i:4;s:9:"greek-ext";i:5;s:9:"latin-ext";i:6;s:12:"cyrillic-ext";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_show_author_inthis_post]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[author_default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_builder_version]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BB|Divi|3.2.2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_thumbnail_id]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[29969]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_wp_old_slug]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[agg-capital]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>GLORIA SUMMER TRAINING</title>
		<link>https://entrena.fi/a-word-on-summer-training/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 11:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://entrena.fi/?p=29333</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[et_pb_section bb_built="1" specialty="off" _builder_version="3.2.2"][et_pb_row _builder_version="3.0.96"][et_pb_column type="4_4"][et_pb_text admin_label="blog post model" max_width="560px" text_line_height_last_edited="on|phone" use_border_color="off" header_font_size="40px" text_font_size="16" text_line_height="1.6em" text_line_height_tablet="1.7em" header_text_color="#0c71c3" background_position="top_left" background_repeat="repeat" background_size="initial" _builder_version="3.2.2" text_font="Verdana||||||||" text_font_size_last_edited="on|phone" header_font_size_last_edited="on|desktop"]

Off-season training is the best opportunity to develop strength in AGG for a variety of reasons.

Every team has a different approach, and all of them have pros and cons.

The following is what works for Gloria, last season bronze at the Finnish nationals and this year transitioning to women's category. Keep reading.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>The Summer</strong></h3>
Firstly, notice that during summer gymnasts are well rested -no high school- and in a better mood than usual: Sun in Finland!

Opportunities to increase intensity without risking injury are rare; therefore I try to seize this moment.

In-season, lack of time for strength training and high academic stress is the norm.

However, if you build a strong base in summer, you can maintain most of it during the season.

Trying to improve both choreography and strength won't play out well: one ass cannot sit on two horses.

Furthermore, as gymnasts grow older, they accumulate injuries. Some are forced to retire early or train in constant pain.

Gloria has been successful in the past at avoiding injuries, but the best prevention is always getting stronger. Read on.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>What we do</strong></h3>
One month of running in the park and home stretching-only is better than nothing, but you will lose any previous strength levels if you avoid resistance training altogether.

Knowing this, I keep "open gym" training during the holidays, where the gymnasts come to build their strength to get ahead before next season.

Most families will not be four full weeks on vacation, so there is no reason to avoid strength training if the gymnasts are in the city.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Stick to the basics</strong></h3>
I don't like wasting valuable athlete's time, so I stick to exercises that are tried and true.

Warmups start with a potent dose of glute "activation" (hip thrusts, mini-band walks) and a combination of unilateral exercises and core stability.

To assess readiness, you can ask them how are they feeling that day, but pay attention to their facial expressions and their quality of movement during warm-up.

Some gymnasts will never say if something is hurting or if they didn't sleep last nite, so you need to read between the lines.

If everything's on point, the main workout consists of a combination of back-to-back pushing and pulling exercises: safety back squats, barbell presses, bench presses, hang power cleans, push presses, rows, trap bar deadlifts...

We keep track of every weight on every set on a blackboard and progress weekly.

When it comes to back strength, I have had success with a variety of exercises, but now I stick to seal rows and pull-ups.

The reason? They are harder to screw up. Gymnasts typically have hyperlordosis and need exercises where their backs can't extend while still being able to train heavy safely.

Pull-ups with proper form are always a good idea (no kipping, slow descent and a full range of motion), but they require consistency.

If a competitive gymnast can't get a single pull-up, you may want to rethink your training plan or pay more attention to the diet.

Other than the barbell exercises, I like to add flywheel training to the mix and improve their eccentric strength.

For those that have never tried it, imagine a force that violently pulls you down unless you push in the opposite direction.

Research consistently shows that flywheel training reduces injuries and improves power and strength better than traditional lifting, so we would be dumb not to use it.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Jumps and Conditioning</strong></h3>
The notion that you improve just by jumping is 100% wrong unless you are completely untrained.

However, hops and jumps in a variety of planes of motion will have an injury prevention effect, and it will show you who is strong and who isn't.

I try to fit these during warm-ups because landing on a single leg when fatigue has already kicked in can have ugly consequences.

Beware of gymnasts with a history of ankle sprains: once somebody tears the ligaments, the likelihood of it happening again is very high.

On top of this, gymnasts have an aerobic plan to do on their own. Instead of going too fancy, I try to use the KISS system (keep it simple, stupid).

A combination of intervals and endurance running will do enough for them during the period.

The goal is not to build a marathoner's engine, but to slightly increase their maximal oxygen consumption to a level where you don't gas out while training your choreography.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Summing up</strong></h3>
The summer is long, and there is plenty of time for ice cream, family, and friends, but it's not an excuse to get out of shape.

If you want to win, your actions need to match your ambitions.

Focus on the only thing that you can control: your effort.

[/et_pb_text][et_pb_social_media_follow follow_button="on" _builder_version="3.2.2" border_radii="on|100%|100%|100%|100%" saved_tabs="all" global_module="29607"][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="instagram" url="https://www.instagram.com/agg_entrena" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#517fa4" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on"]

&lt;p&gt;Instagram&lt;/p&gt;

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="facebook" url="https://www.facebook.com/entrenafi/" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#3b5998" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px" background_video_pause_outside_viewport="on" box_shadow_style="none"]

Facebook

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="youtube" url="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnr5AS5uScFE2hmcGBsJitA" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#a82400" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px"]

Youtube

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][/et_pb_social_media_follow][/et_pb_column][/et_pb_row][/et_pb_section]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[How you can train during the summer.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>29333</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-07-27 14:59:49]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-07-27 11:59:49]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[a-word-on-summer-training]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="strength"><![CDATA[Strength]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_monarch_override]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_color]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[#ffffff]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[light]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_show_title]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_post_hide_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_page_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[et_full_width_page]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_side_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[off]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_use_builder]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_ab_stats_refresh_interval]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hourly]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_old_content]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_enable_shortcode_tracking]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_custom_css]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jetpack_related_posts_cache]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:32:"8f6677c9d6b0f903e98ad32ec61f8deb";a:2:{s:7:"expires";i:1533110010;s:7:"payload";a:3:{i:0;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28796;}i:1;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29355;}i:2;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28792;}}}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_wpas_done_all]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[et_enqueued_post_fonts]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:2:{s:6:"family";a:1:{s:21:"et-gf-source-sans-pro";s:100:"Source+Sans+Pro:200,200italic,300,300italic,regular,italic,600,600italic,700,700italic,900,900italic";}s:6:"subset";a:7:{i:0;s:8:"cyrillic";i:1;s:5:"greek";i:2;s:10:"vietnamese";i:3;s:5:"latin";i:4;s:9:"greek-ext";i:5;s:9:"latin-ext";i:6;s:12:"cyrillic-ext";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_builder_version]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BB|Divi|3.2.2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_show_author_inthis_post]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[author_default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_thumbnail_id]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[29937]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>AN INTERESTING REVIEW ON BACK FLEXIBILITY</title>
		<link>https://entrena.fi/back-flexibility-in-agg/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2017 17:13:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sergio.Navadijo]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://entrena.fi/?p=29355</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[et_pb_section bb_built="1" specialty="off" _builder_version="3.2.2"][et_pb_row _builder_version="3.0.96"][et_pb_column type="4_4"][et_pb_text admin_label="blog post model" max_width="560px" text_line_height_last_edited="on|phone" use_border_color="off" header_font_size="40px" text_font_size="16" text_line_height="1.6em" text_line_height_tablet="1.7em" header_text_color="#0c71c3" background_position="top_left" background_repeat="repeat" background_size="initial" _builder_version="3.2.2" text_font="Verdana||||||||" text_font_size_last_edited="on|phone" header_font_size_last_edited="on|desktop"]

General strength is the number one thing that AGG teams lack.

But a gymnast won't make it far without being flexible. I try to stay up to date with gymnastic research, and lately, <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs40279-015-0424-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this study</a> got my attention.

It mainly discusses high-speed back-bends like the ones we see in AGG.

The document talks about the effects of stretching the spine of young gymnasts and its consequences.

I quote and comment them with the help of some photos:
<blockquote><em>"Moving to and from the back-bend position requires a</em>
<em>dynamic spine hyperextension. In all such movements, the</em>
<em>hyperextension should begin with shoulder hyperflexion</em>
<em>(the arms moving behind the head) and superior spine</em>
<em>hyperextension. When the gymnast begins to lower</em>
<em>backward from a stand to a back-bend, the superior spine</em>
<em>hyperextension begins at the superior torso and proceeds</em>
<em>incrementally from the most superior to the most inferior</em>
<em>vertebrae"</em></blockquote>
In simpler words: bend from your upper back, not from your lower back.

Figure 1 is encouraged, and you should avoid backbends like the one in figure 2.

Sadly, Figure 3 is the most common posture we see in AGG gymnasts:

[caption id="attachment_29363" align="alignnone" width="300"]<a href="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/fig1.jpg"><img class="wp-image-29363 size-medium" src="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/fig1-300x224.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="224" /></a> Fig. 1 Back-bend position emphasizing hyperextension in the thoracic spine and shoulder hyperflexion.[/caption]

&nbsp;

[caption id="attachment_29364" align="alignnone" width="300"]<a href="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/fig2.jpg"><img class="wp-image-29364 size-medium" src="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/fig2-300x224.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="224" /></a> Fig. 2 Back-bend position emphasizing hyperextension in the lumbar spine.[/caption]

&nbsp;

[caption id="attachment_29365" align="alignnone" width="300"]<a href="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/fig3.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-29365" src="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/fig3-300x198.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="198" /></a> Fig. 3<br />Young gymnasts performing warmup stretching of their spines. Note the poor positions and the lack of emphasis on placing the majority of the spinal extension in the shoulders and upper back.[/caption]
<blockquote><em>"Bouchard et al. indicated heritability values of 0.69</em>
<em>for low back flexibility in 11- to 15-year-old males and</em>
<em>0.84 for trunk flexibility in male and female twins aged</em>
<em>12–17 years. Other heritability values for flexibility were</em>
<em>0.84 for the trunk, 0.70 for the hip and 0.91 for the</em>
<em>shoulder. Bouchard et al. concluded that genetics may</em>
<em>have a bi influence on flexibility than on</em>
<em>strength. Long-term athlete development programmes have suggested critical</em>
<em>periods for flexibility development, particularly between</em>
<em>the ages of 6 and 11 years" </em></blockquote>
I see coaches and parents wanting girls to compete at a high level.

While we all want to achieve great things, high-level gymnastics is not for everyone.

Extreme back-bends require a set of genetics that most of us don't have.

On top of this, you should do almost all flexibility development at a very young age and maintain it throughout your teenage years.

Trying to stretch a gymnast that doesn't have the proper body structure for extreme bendings won't go well.

It will irritate joints and tissues.

However, and this is only my observation, some gymnasts can compensate for poor flexibility with hard work in other areas that are more trainable, like strength and power.

Others can <strong>learn new movements and choreographies quick</strong>, which is the most significant factor of success in AGG.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>How to be flexible</strong></h3>
In general, if you want to be flexible for AGG you need 2 things:
<ul>
 	<li>Choose the right parents (flexible ones).</li>
 	<li>Stretch a lot between 6 and 11 years old.</li>
</ul>
It may sound depressing, but that's what it comes down to.

Stretching in later stages can have a positive effect, but it will be painful and it won't overcome anatomical limitations.

&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Hypermobile gymnasts and injury</strong></h3>
Notice below another example of back-bending from the low back instead of the upper-back:

[caption id="attachment_29366" align="alignnone" width="225"]<a href="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/40279_2015_424_Fig6_HTML.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-29366" src="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/40279_2015_424_Fig6_HTML-225x300.jpg" alt="" width="225" height="300" /></a> Fig. 6<br />Signature position when ending a routine. The gymnast shows a hyperextended cervical, thoracic and lumbar spine. The hyperextension is particularly dramatic in the lumbar spine.[/caption]
<blockquote><em>"In a study of the</em>
<em>Royal Ballet School in London and 53 student nurse controls,</em>
<em>the results indicated that ballet students showed a</em>
<em>higher incidence of hypermobility of joints—including the</em>
<em>spine, hips, and ankles—which would clearly be desirable</em>
<em>and influenced by training. However, the dancers also</em>
<em>showed greater joint hypermobility in the knees, elbows and</em>
<em>wrists, which is not desirable and should not be enhanced by</em>
<em>training." </em></blockquote>
The same reason that makes coaches select you for gymnastics also predisposes you to injury.

Many gymnasts that appear flexible suffer from excessively mobile joints and a lack of control of them.
<blockquote><em>"Dancers had to learn to consciously limit their excessive</em>
<em>range of movement by voluntary muscle control. Dancers also</em>
<em>appeared to suffer more ligamentous injury and stress</em>
<em>fractures, thus showing that JHS may be a mixed blessing." </em></blockquote>
Gaining stability is easier said than done.

Telling a hypermobile person not to be hypermobile is like telling a cat not to cat.

It's possible to improve motor control and strength, but the risk of injury is always there.

[caption id="attachment_29367" align="alignnone" width="225"]<a href="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/40279_2015_424_Fig7_HTML.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-29367" src="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/40279_2015_424_Fig7_HTML-225x300.jpg" alt="" width="225" height="300" /></a> Fig. 7<br />Hyperextended knee[/caption]

[caption id="attachment_29368" align="alignnone" width="300"]<a href="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/40279_2015_424_Fig8_HTML.jpg"><img class="size-medium wp-image-29368" src="https://entrena.fi/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/40279_2015_424_Fig8_HTML-300x224.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="224" /></a> Fig. 8<br />Hyperextended elbow[/caption]

Training volume increases risk of injury:
<blockquote><em>"A study of highly trained female gymnasts and swimmers</em>
<em>showed that gymnasts had a greater incidence of</em>
<em>spinal abnormalities that were correlated with training</em>
<em>hours. One can </em><em>likely assume that symptomatic spine problems </em><em>arising in</em>
<em>late childhood, early adolescence and young adulthood had</em>
<em>their origins at younger ages. More gymnasts than</em>
<em>controls had injury symptoms in the wrist, low back, hip,</em>
<em>shin and foot. Gymnasts had an average of 6.17 symptomatic</em>
<em>regions, versus 2.25 in controls" </em></blockquote>
Also, there is evidence that the price to pay is higher than other sports:
<blockquote><em>" A 1991 study comparing gymnasts</em>
<em>and swimmers showed that 9 % of pre-elite, 43 % of</em>
<em>elite and 63 % of Olympic gymnasts had spinal abnormalities,</em>
<em>versus only 15.8 % of swimmers".</em></blockquote>
&nbsp;
<h3><strong>Take home points</strong></h3>
What can we take home about all this?

While there is no perfect method, we can at least minimize the risks that go along with gymnastics by doing two things:

1. <strong>Stretch with proper form</strong> and only demand what's possible.

Ask only for extreme backbends if the gymnast can do it with good form.

Remember not everyone will be able to do it due to structural limitations.

Some girls will never be ready: they don't have the anatomical structure that allows their spine to bend without compensating at the low back.

While we want to encourage all children to do the sport that they love, gymnastics has high risks.

Demand just what seems plausible, nothing less and nothing more.

2. <strong>Get stronger. </strong>I may be biased here, so instead I will quote the study:
<blockquote><em>"A study of rhythmic gymnasts aged 13–19 years showed</em>
<em>that youth, greater leanness, non-smoking, less anxious or</em>
<em>depressive behavior, and increased muscle strength and</em>
<em>flexibility all represented preventive factors for low back</em>
<em>pain." </em></blockquote>
In other words, strength train is the primary factor that coaches can affect, with the other elements being genetical and environmental.

Gymnasts don't need to do more jumps, they need more strength.

With more strength, they will jump higher and have fewer injuries.

More jumping will only cause more repetitive stress, and you won't jump any higher.

Lifting weights won't make you automatically gain a ton of muscle, which seems a concern from coaches.

Even if it did, that is still better than being hurt and having weak jumps.

All studies are subject to interpretation.

The review goes much more in depth, so I encourage you to read it for yourself and form your own opinion.

[/et_pb_text][et_pb_social_media_follow follow_button="on" _builder_version="3.2.2" border_radii="on|100%|100%|100%|100%" saved_tabs="all" global_module="29607"][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="instagram" url="https://www.instagram.com/agg_entrena" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#517fa4" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on"]

&lt;p&gt;Instagram&lt;/p&gt;

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="facebook" url="https://www.facebook.com/entrenafi/" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#3b5998" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px" background_video_pause_outside_viewport="on" box_shadow_style="none"]

Facebook

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][et_pb_social_media_follow_network social_network="youtube" url="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCnr5AS5uScFE2hmcGBsJitA" _builder_version="3.2.2" background_color="#a82400" follow_button="on" url_new_window="on" skype_action="call" use_background_color_gradient="off" background_color_gradient_start="#2b87da" background_color_gradient_end="#29c4a9" background_color_gradient_type="linear" background_color_gradient_direction="180deg" background_color_gradient_direction_radial="center" background_color_gradient_start_position="0%" background_color_gradient_end_position="100%" background_color_gradient_overlays_image="off" parallax="off" parallax_method="on" background_size="cover" background_position="center" background_repeat="no-repeat" background_blend="normal" allow_player_pause="off" border_radii="on|3px|3px|3px|3px"]

Youtube

[/et_pb_social_media_follow_network][/et_pb_social_media_follow][/et_pb_column][/et_pb_row][/et_pb_section]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Stretching the spine in AGG.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>29355</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-10-25 20:13:41]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-10-25 17:13:41]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[back-flexibility-in-agg]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="flexibility"><![CDATA[Flexibility]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_monarch_override]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_color]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[#ffffff]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_post_bg_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[light]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_show_title]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_post_hide_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_page_layout]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[et_full_width_page]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_side_nav]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[off]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_use_builder]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[on]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_ab_stats_refresh_interval]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hourly]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_old_content]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_enable_shortcode_tracking]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_pb_custom_css]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jetpack_related_posts_cache]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:32:"8f6677c9d6b0f903e98ad32ec61f8deb";a:2:{s:7:"expires";i:1533503429;s:7:"payload";a:3:{i:0;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28790;}i:1;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:29257;}i:2;a:1:{s:2:"id";i:28800;}}}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_wpas_done_all]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[et_enqueued_post_fonts]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:2:{s:6:"family";a:1:{s:21:"et-gf-source-sans-pro";s:100:"Source+Sans+Pro:200,200italic,300,300italic,regular,italic,600,600italic,700,700italic,900,900italic";}s:6:"subset";a:7:{i:0;s:8:"cyrillic";i:1;s:5:"greek";i:2;s:10:"vietnamese";i:3;s:5:"latin";i:4;s:9:"greek-ext";i:5;s:9:"latin-ext";i:6;s:12:"cyrillic-ext";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_et_builder_version]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[BB|Divi|3.2.2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_show_author_inthis_post]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[author_default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_thumbnail_id]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[29366]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
